<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY rfc3339 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml">
        <!ENTITY rfc3743 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3743.xml">
        <!ENTITY rfc5646 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml">
        <!ENTITY rfc4290 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4290.xml">
        <!ENTITY rfc5564 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5564.xml">
        <!ENTITY rfc5892 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5892.xml">
        ]>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-davies-idntables-08">
    <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
    <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
    <?rfc strict="no" ?>

    <front>
        <title abbrev="Label Generation Rulesets in XML">Representing Label Generation Rulesets
            using XML</title>
        <author initials="K" surname="Davies" fullname="Kim Davies">
            <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
                Numbers</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>12025 Waterfront Drive</street>
                    <city>Los Angeles</city>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <code>90094</code>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+1 310 301 5800</phone>
                <email>kim.davies@icann.org</email>
                <uri>http://www.icann.org/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="A" surname="Freytag" fullname="Asmus Freytag">
            <organization>ASMUS Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <email>asmus@unicode.org</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date/>
        <area>Management</area>
        <abstract>
            <t>This document describes a method of representing rules for validating identifier
                labels and alternate representations of those labels using Extensible Markup
                Language (XML). These policies, known as "Label Generation Rulesets" (LGRs), are
                used for the implementation of Internationalized Domain Names (IDNs), for example.
                The rulesets are used to implement and share that aspect of policy defining which
                labels and specific Unicode code points are permitted for registrations, which
                alternative code points are considered variants, and what actions may be performed
                on labels containing those variants. </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>

        <section title="Introduction">

            <t>This memo describes a method of using Extensible Markup Language (XML) to describe
                the algorithm used to determine whether a given identifier label is permitted, and
                under which conditions, based on the code points it contains and their context.
                These algorithms are comprised of a list of permissible code points, variant code
                point mappings, and a set of rules acting on them. These algorithms form part of an
                administrator's policies, and can be referred to as Label Generation Rulesets
                (LGRs), or IDN tables. </t>
            <t>There are other kinds policies relating to labels which are not normally covered by
                Label Generation Rulesets and are therefore not representable by the XML format
                described here. These include, but are not limited to policies around trademarks, or
                prohibition of fraudulent or objectionable words. </t>
            <t>Administrators of the zones for top-level domain registries have historically
                published their LGRs using ASCII text or HTML. The formatting of these documents has
                been loosely based on the format used for the Language Variant Table in <xref
                    target="RFC3743"/>. <xref target="RFC4290"/> also provides a "model table
                format" that describes a similar set of functionality. Common to these formats is
                that the algorithms used to evaluate the data therein are implicit or specified
                elsewhere. </t>
            <t>Through the first decade of IDN deployment, experience has shown that LGRs derived
                from these formats are difficult to consistently implement and compare due to their
                differing formats. A universal format, such as one using a structured XML format,
                will assist by improving machine-readability, consistency, reusability and
                maintainability of LGRs. </t>
            <t>When used to represent simple list of permitted code points, the format is quite
                straightforward. At the cost of some complexity in the resulting file, it also
                allows for an implementation of more sophisticated handling of conditional variants
                that reflects the known requirements of current zone administrator policies. </t>
            <t>Another feature of this format is that it allows many of the algorithms to be made
                explicit and machine implementable. A remaining small set of implicit algorithms is
                described in this document to allow commonality in implementation. </t>
            <t>While the predominant usage of this specification is to represent IDN label policy,
                the format is not limited to IDN usage may also be used for describing ASCII domain
                name label rulesets, or other identifier labels beyond domain names. </t>

        </section>

        <section title="Design Goals">

            <t>The following goals informed the design of this format:</t>
            <t>
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>The format needs to be implementable in a reasonably straightforward manner
                        in software. </t>
                    <t>The format should be able to be checked for formatting errors, so that
                        common mistakes can be caught. </t>
                    <t>An LGR needs to be able to express the set of valid code points that are
                        allowed for registration under a specific zone administrator's policies. </t>
                    <t>Provide the ability to express computed alternatives to a given domain name
                        based on mapping relationships between code points, whether one-to-one or
                        many-to-many. These computed alternatives are commonly known as "variants". </t>
                    <t>Variant code points should be able to be tagged with specific dispositions or
                        categories that can be used to support registry policy (such as whether to
                        allocate the computed variant in the zone, or to merely block it from
                        registration). </t>
                    <t>Variants and code points must be able to stipulated based on contextual
                        information. For example, specific variants may only be applicable when they
                        follow another specific code point, or when the code point is displayed in a
                        specific presentation form. </t>
                    <t>The data contained within an LGR must be able to be interpreted
                        unambiguously, so that independent implementations that utilize the
                        contents will arrive at the same results. </t>
                    <t>To the largest extent possible, policy rules should be able to be specified
                        in the XML format without relying hidden, or built-in algorithms in
                        implementations.</t>
                    <t>LGRs should be suitable for comparison and re-use, such that one could easily
                        compare the contents of two or more to see the differences, to merge them,
                        and so on. </t>
                    <t>As many existing IDN tables as practicable should be able to be migrated to
                        the LGR format with all applicable interpretation logic retained. </t>
                </list>
            </t>

            <t>These requirements are partly derived from reviewing the existing corpus of published
                IDN tables, plus the requirements of ICANN's work to implement an LGR for the DNS
                Root Zone <xref target="LGR-PROCEDURE"/>. In particular, Section B of that document
                identifies five specific requirements for an LGR methodology. </t>
            <t>The syntax and rules in <xref target="RFC5892"/> and <xref target="RFC3743"/> were
                also reviewed. </t>

            <t>It is explicitly not the goal of this format to stipulate what code points should be
                listed in an LGR by a zone administrator. Which registration policies are used for a
                particular zone is outside the scope of this memo. </t>

        </section>



        <section title="LGR Format">

            <t>An LGR is expressed as a well-formed XML Document <xref target="XML"/>. </t>

            <section title="Namespace">

                <t>The XML Namespace URI is [TBD]. [Note: the examples and schemas for any non-final
                    versions of this specification use a temporary namespace]</t>

            </section>

            <section title="Basic Structure">

                <t>The basic XML framework of the document is as follows:</t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[
    <?xml version="1.0"?>
    <lgr xmlns="http://www.iana.org/lgr/0.1">
        ...
    </lgr>]]></artwork>
                </figure>

                <t>Within the "lgr" element rest several sub-elements. First is an optional "meta"
                    element that contains all meta-data associated with the LGR, such as its
                    authorship, what it is used for, implementation notes and references. This is
                    followed by a "data" element that contains the substantive code point data.
                    Finally, an optional "rules" element contains information on contextual and
                    whole-label evaluation rules, if any, along with any specific "action" elements
                    providing for the disposition of labels and computed variant labels. </t>

                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[
    <?xml version="1.0"?>
    <lgr xmlns="http://www.iana.org/lgr/0.1">
        <meta>
            ...
        </meta>
        <data>
            ...
        </data>
        <rules>
            ...
        </rules>
    </lgr>
]]></artwork>
                </figure>

                <t>A document MUST contain exactly one "lgr" element. Each "lgr" element MUST
                    contain exactly one "data" element, optionally preceded by one "meta" element
                    and optionally followed by one "rules" element. </t>
                <t>In the following descriptions, required, non-repeating elements or attributes are
                    generally not called out explicitly, in contrast to optional ones or those that
                    may be repeated. For attributes that take lists as values the elements are
                    space-delimited. </t>

            </section>
            <section title="Metadata">

                <t>The optional "meta" element is used to express meta-data associated within the
                    LGR. It can be used to identify the author or relevant contact person, explain
                    the intended usage of the LGR, and provide implementation notes as well as
                    references. The data contained within is not required by software consuming the
                    LGR in order to calculate valid labels, or to calculate variants. However, the
                    "unicode-version" element MUST be used by a consumer of the table to identify
                    that it has the correct Unicode property data to perform operations on the
                    table. </t>

                <section title="The version Element">

                    <t>The "version" element is optional. It is used to uniquely identify each
                        version of the LGR. No specific format is required, but it is RECOMMENDED
                        that it be the decimal representation of a single positive
                        integer, which is incremented with each revision of the file. </t>

                    <t>An example of a typical first edition of a document:</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
    <version>1</version>
    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>The "version" element may have an optional "comment" attribute.</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
    <version comment="draft">1</version>
    ]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="The date Element">

                    <t>The optional "date" element is used to identify the date the LGR was posted.
                        The contents of this element MUST be a valid ISO 8601 full-date string as
                        described in <xref target="RFC3339"/>. </t>

                    <figure>
                        <preamble>Example of a date:</preamble>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
    <date>2009-11-01</date>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                </section>
                <section title="The language Element">

                    <t>The optional "language" element signals that the LGR is associated with a
                        specific language or script. The value of the "language" element MUST be a
                        valid language tag as described in <xref target="RFC5646"/>. The tag may
                        refer to a script plus undefined language if the LGR is not referring to a
                        specific language. </t>

                    <t>Example of an English language LGR:</t>

                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
   <language>en</language>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

                    <t>If the LGR applies to a specific script, rather than a language, the "und"
                        language tag should be used followed by the relevant <xref target="RFC5646"
                        /> script subtag. For example, for a Cyrillic script LGR: </t>

                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
   <language>und-Cyrl</language>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>If the LGR covers a specific set of multiple languages or scripts, the
                        "language" element can be repeated. However, for cases of a script-specific
                        LGR exhibiting insignificant admixture of code points from other scripts, it
                        is RECOMMENDED to the use a single "language" element identifying the
                        predominant script. In the exceptional case of a multi-script LGR where no
                        script is predominant, use Zyyy (Common): </t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
   <language>und-Zyyy</language>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>Note that that for the particular case of Japanese, a script tag "Jpan"
                        exists that matches the mixture of scripts used in writing that language.
                        The preferred "language" element would be: </t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
   <language>und-Jpan</language>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>

                <section title="The scope Element">

                    <t>This optional element refers to a scope, such as a domain, to which this
                        policy is applied. The "type" attribute specifies the type of scope being
                        defined. A type of "domain" means that the scope is a domain that represents
                        the apex of the zone to which the LGR is applied. The value must be a valid
                        domain name, and in the case of the root zone, should be represented as ".".
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <scope type="domain">example.com</scope>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>

                    <t>There may be multiple "scope" tags used, for example to reflect a list of domains
                        to which the LGR is applied. Other types of scope are application defined, with
                        an explanation in the "description" element RECOMMENDED.</t>

                </section>
                <section title="The description Element">

                    <t>The "description" element is an optional free-form element that contains any
                        additional relevant description that is useful for the user in its
                        interpretation. Typically, this field contains authorship information, as
                        well as additional context on how the LGR was formulated and how it applies,
                        such as citations and references that apply to the LGR as a whole.</t>

                    <t>The element has an optional "type" attribute, which refers to the internet
                        media type of the enclosed data. Typical types would be "text/plain" or
                        "text/html". The attribute SHOULD be a valid MIME type. If supplied, it will
                        be assumed the contents is content of that media type. If the description
                        lacks a type field, it will be assumed to be plain text ("text/plain"). </t>

                </section>

                <section title="The validity-start and validity-end Elements">

                    <t>The "validity-start" and "validity-end" elements are optional elements that
                        describe the time period from which the contents of the LGR become valid
                        (i.e. are used in registry policy), and the contents of the LGR cease to be
                        used. </t>
                    <t>The dates MUST confirm to the "full-date" format described in section 5.6 of
                            <xref target="RFC3339"/>.</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <validity-start>2014-03-12</validity-start>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="The unicode-version Element">

                    <t>Whenever an LGR depends on character properties from a given version of the
                        Unicode standard, the version number used in creating the LGR MUST be listed
                        in the form x.y.z, where x, y, and z are positive, decimal integers (see
                            <xref target="Unicode-Versions"/>). If any software processing the table
                        does not have access to character property data of the requisite version, it
                        MUST NOT perform any operations relating to whole-label evaluation relying
                        on Unicode properties (<xref target="property"/>).</t>
                    <t> The value of a given Unicode property in <xref target="UAX42"/> may change
                        between versions, unless such change has been explicitly disallowed in <xref
                            target="Unicode-Stability"/>. It is RECOMMENDED to only reference properties
                        defined as stable or immutable. As an alternative to referencing the property,
                        the information can be presented explicitly in the LGR.</t>

                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <unicode-version>6.2.0</unicode-version>
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>It is not necessary to include a "unicode-version" element for LGRs that do
                        not make use of Unicode properties, however, it is RECOMMENDED. </t>
                </section>
                <section title="The references Element" anchor="references">
                    <t>A Label Generation Ruleset may define a list of references which are used to
                       associate various individual elements in the LGR to one or more normative
                       references. A common use for references is to annotate that code points belong
                       to an externally defined collection or standard, or to give normative references
                       for rules.</t>
                    <t>References are specified in an optional "references" element contains any
                        number of "reference" elements, each with a unique "id" attribute. It is
                        RECOMMENDED that the "id" attribute be an zero-based integer. The value of
                        each "reference" element SHOULD be the citation of a standard, dictionary or
                        other specification in any suitable format. In addition to an "id"
                        attribute, a "reference" element may have a "comment" attribute for an
                        optional free-form annotation. </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <references>
      <reference id="0">The Unicode Standard, Version 7.0</reference>
      <reference id="1">Big-5: Computer Chinese Glyph and Character
         Code Mapping Table, Technical Report C-26, 1984</reference>
      <reference id="2" comment="synchronized with Unicode 6.1">
         ISO/IEC
         10646:2012 3rd edition</reference>
      ...
    </references>
    ...
    <data>
      <char cp="0620" ref="0 2" />
      ...
    </data>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t> A reference is associated with an element by using an optional "ref" attribute
                        (see <xref target="ref"/>).  The use of "ref" attributes is limited to certain
                        kinds of elements in the "data" or "rules" sections of the LGR, most notably
                        those defining code points and rules. A "ref" attribute may not occur on elements
                        that are named references to character classes and rules nor on certain other
                        element types. See description of these elements below.</t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Code Points and Variants">

            <t>The bulk of a label generation ruleset is a description of which set of code points
                are eligible for a given label. For rulesets that perform operations that result in
                potential variants, the code point-level relationships between variants need to also
                be described. </t>

            <t>The code point data is collected within the "data" element. Within this element, a
                series of "char" and "range" elements describe eligible code points, or ranges of
                code points, respectively. </t>

            <t>Discrete permissible code points or code point sequences are declared with a "char"
                element, e.g.</t>

            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="002D"/>]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>

            <t>Ranges of permissible code points may be stipulated with a "range" element, e.g.</t>

            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[    <range first-cp="0030" last-cp="0039"/>]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>

            <t>The range is inclusive of the first and last code points.  All attributes defined
                for a "range" element act as if applied to each code point within. A "range" element
                has no child elements.</t>
            <t>It is always possible to substitute a list of individually specified code points for
                a range element. The reverse is not necessarily the case.  Whenever a such a
                substitution is possible, it makes no difference in processing the data and tools
                reading or writing the XML format are free to make it. </t>
            <t>Code points must be expressed in uppercase, hexadecimal, and zero padded to a minimum
                of 4 digits - in other words according to the standard Unicode convention but
                without the prefix "U+". The rationale for not allowing other encoding formats,
                including native Unicode encoding in XML, is explored in <xref target="UAX42"/>. The
                XML conventions used in this format, including the element and attribute names,
                mirror this document where practical and reasonable to do so. It is RECOMMENDED to
                list all "char" elements in ascending order of the "cp" attribute. </t>
            <t>All "char" elements in the data section MUST have distinct "cp" attributes. The
                "range" elements MUST NOT specify code point ranges that overlap either another range
                or any single code point "char" elements.</t>

            <section title="Sequences" anchor="sequences">

                <t>A sequence of two or more code points may be specified in a LGR, for example,
                    when defining the source for n:m variant mappings. Another use of sequences
                    would be in cases when the exact sequence of code points is required to occur in
                    order for the constituent elements to be eligible, such as when a specific code
                    point is only eligible when preceded or followed by another code point. The
                    following would define the eligibility of the MIDDLE DOT (U+00B7) only when both
                    preceded and followed by the LATIN SMALL LETTER L (U+006C): </t>

                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="006C 00B7 006C" comment="Catalan middle dot"/>]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t>All sequences defined this way must be distinct, but sub-sequences may be defined.
                    Thus, the sequence defined here may coexist with single code point definitions
                    such as:</t>
                <t><figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="006C" />]]></artwork>
                </figure></t>
                <t>As an alternative to using sequences to define a required context, a "char" or
                    "range" element may specify conditional context using an optional "when"
                    attribute as described below in <xref target="when"/>. The latter method is more
                    flexible in that such conditional context is not limited to specific code point
                    in addition to allowing both prohibited as well as required context to be
                    specified. </t>
                <t>As described below, the "char" element, whether or not it is used for a single
                    code point, or for a sequence, may have optional child elements defining
                    variants. Both the "char" and "range" elements can take a number of optional
                    attributes for conditional inclusion, commenting, cross referencing and
                    character tagging, as described below.</t>
            </section>

            <section title="Variants">

                <t>Most LGRs typically only determine simple code point eligibility, and for them,
                    the elements described so far would be the only ones required for their "data"
                    section. Others additionally specify a mapping of code points to other code
                    points, known as "variants". What constitutes a variant code point is a matter
                    of policy, and varies for each implementation. The following examples are
                    intended to demonstrate the syntax; they are not necessarily typical. </t>

                <section title="Basic Variants">
                    <t>Variant code points are specified using one of more "var" elements as
                        children of a "char" element. The target mapping is specified using the "cp"
                        attribute. Other, optional attributes for the "var" element are described
                        below.</t>
                    <t>For example, to map LATIN SMALL LETTER V (U+0076) as a variant of LATIN SMALL
                        LETTER U (U+0075): </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="0075">
        <var cp="0076"/>
    </char>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>A sequence of multiple code points can be specified as a variant of a single
                        code point. For example, the sequence of LATIN SMALL LETTER O (U+006F) then
                        LATIN SMALL LETTER E (U+0065) might hypothetically be specified as a variant
                        for an LATIN SMALL LETTER O WITH DIAERESIS (U+00F6) as follows: </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="00F6">
        <var cp="006F 0065"/>
    </char>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>

                    <t>The "var" element specifies variant mappings in only one direction, even
                        though the variant relation is usually considered symmetric, that is, if A
                        is a variant of B then B should also be a variant of A. The format requires
                        that the inverse of the variant be given explicitly to fully specify
                        symmetric variant relations in the LGR. This has the beneficial side effect
                        of making the symmetry explicit: </t>

                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="006F 0065">
        <var cp="00F6"/>
    </char>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>

                    <t>Both the source and target of a variant mapping may be sequences, but not
                        ranges.</t>
                    <t>All variant mappings are unique. For a given "char" element all "var" elements
                        MUST have a unique combination of "cp" , "when" and "not-when" attributes.
                        It is RECOMMENDED to list the  "var" elements  in ascending order of their
                        target code point sequence. (For "when" and "not-when" attributes, see
                        <xref target="when" />).</t>
                </section>

                <section title="The type attribute" anchor="var_type">

                    <t>Variants may be tagged with an optional "type" attribute. The value of the
                        "type" attribute may be any non-empty  value not starting with an underscore
                        and not containing spaces.  This value is used to resolve the disposition of
                        any variant labels created using a given variant. (See
                        <xref target="variants_actions" />.)</t>
                    <t>By default, the values of the "type" attribute more or less directly describe
                        the policy state (disposition) for a variant label that was generated using
                        a particular variant, with any variant label being assigned a disposition
                        corresponding to the most restrictive variant type. Several conventional
                        disposition values are predefined below in  <xref target="actions"/>. Whenever
                        these values can represent the desired policy, they SHOULD be used.
                    </t>
                    <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="767C">
        <var cp="53D1" type="allocate"/>
        <var cp="5F42" type="block"/>
        <var cp="9AEA" type="block"/>
        <var cp="9AEE" type="block"/>
    </char>]]></artwork>
                    </figure></t>
                    <t>By default, if a variant label contains any instance of one of the variants of
                        type "blocked" the label would be blocked, but if it contained only instances
                        of variants to be allocated it could be allocated. See the discussion about
                        implied actions in <xref target="default_actions"/>.
                    </t>
                    <t>The XML format for the LGR makes the relation between the values of the "type"
                        attribute on variants and the resulting disposition of variant labels fully
                        explicit. See the discussion in <xref target="variants_actions" />. Making
                        this relation explicit allows a generalization of the "type" attribute from
                        directly reflecting dispositions to a more differentiated intermediate value
                        that used in the resolution of label disposition. Instead of the default
                        action of applying the most restrictive disposition to the entire label, such
                        a generalized resolution can be used to achieve additional goals, such as
                        limiting the set of allocated variant labels, or to implement other policies
                        found in existing LGRs (see for example <xref target="translate_rfc3743" />).
                    </t>
                    <t>Because variant mappings MUST be unique, it is not possible to define the same
                        variant for the same "char" element with different type attributes (see however
                        <xref target="when" />).</t>
                </section>

                <section title="Null Variants">

                    <t>To specify a null variant, which is a variant string that maps to no code
                        point, use an empty cp attribute. For example, to mark a string with a ZERO
                        WIDTH NON-JOINER (U+200C) to the same string without the ZERO WIDTH
                        NON-JOINER: </t>

                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="200C">
        <var cp=""/>
    </char>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>This is useful in expressing the intent that some code points in a label are
                        to be mapped away when generating a canonical variant of the label. However,
                        in tables that are designed to have symmetric variant mappings, this could
                        lead to combinatorial explosion, if not handled carefully.</t>

                    <t>The symmetric form of a null variant is expressed as follows:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="">
        <var cp="200C" type="invalid" />
    </char>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>A "char" element with an empty "cp" attribute MUST specify at least one variant
                        mapping. It is strongly RECOMMENDED to use a type of "invalid" or equivalent
                        when defining variant mappings from null sequences, so that variant mapping from
                        null sequences are removed in variant label generation (see <xref
                                target="var_type" />).</t>
                </section>

                <section title="Variants with Reflexive Mapping" anchor="reflexive_mapping">
                    <t>At first sight there seems to be no call for adding variant mappings for which
                        source and target code points are the same, that is for which the mapping is
                        reflexive, or, in other words, an identity mapping. Yet such reflexive mappings
                        occur frequently in LGRs that follow <xref target="RFC3743"/>.</t>
                    <t>Adding a "var" element allows both a type and a reference id to be specified for
                        it. While the reference id is not used in processing, the type of the variant
                        can be used to trigger actions. In permuting the label to generate all possible
                        variants, the type associated with a reflexive variant mapping is applied to any
                        of the permuted labels containing the original code point.</t>
                    <t>In the following example, the code point U+3473 exists both as a variant of U+3447
                        and as a variant of itself (reflexive mapping). Assuming an original label of
                        "U+3473 U+3447", the permuted variant "U+3473 U+3473" would consist of the reflexive
                        variant of U+3473 followed by a variant of U+3447. Accordingly, the
                        types for both of the variant mappings used to generate that particular
                        permutation would have the value "preferred" given the following definitions
                        of variant mappings:</t>
                    <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[     <char cp="3447" ref="0">
      <var cp="3473" type="preferred" ref="1 3" />
    </char>
    <char cp="3473" ref="0">
      <var cp="3447" type="block" ref="1 3" />
      <var cp="3473" type="preferred" ref="0" />
    </char>]]></artwork>
                    </figure></t>
                    <t>Having established the variant types in this way, a set of actions could be defined
                        that return a disposition of "allocate" or "activate" for a label consisting
                        exclusively of variants with type "preferred" for example. (For details on how to
                        define actions based on variant types see <xref target="actions"/>.)</t>
                    <t>In general, using reflexive variant mappings in this manner makes it possible to
                        calculate disposition values using a uniform approach for all labels, whether they
                        consist of mapped variant code points, original code points, or a mixture of both.
                        In particular, the dispositions for two otherwise identical labels may differ based
                        on which variant mappings were executed in order to generate each of them. (For
                        details on how to generate variants and evaluate dispositions, see
                        <xref target="processing" />.)</t>
                </section>

                <section title="Conditional Variants" anchor="when">
                    <t>Fundamentally, variants are mappings between two sequences of code points.
                        However, in some instances for a variant relationship to exist, some context
                        external to the code point sequence must be considered. For example, a
                        positional context may determine whether two code point sequences are
                        variants of each other. </t>

                    <t>An example of that are Arabic code points which can have different forms
                        based on position, with some code points sharing forms, thus making them
                        variants in the positions corresponding to those forms. Such positional
                        context cannot be solely derived from the code point by itself, as the code
                        point would be the same for the various forms. </t>

                    <t>To specify a conditional variant relationship the optional "when" attribute
                        is used. The variant relationship exists when the condition in the "when"
                        attribute is satisfied. A "not-when" attribute may be used for conditions
                        that must not be satisfied. The value of each "when" or "not-when"
                        attributes is a parameterized context rule as described below in <xref
                            target="parameterized_context_rule"/>. </t>
                    <t>Assuming the "rules" element contains suitably defined rules for
                        "arabic-isolated" and "arabic-final", the following example shows how to
                        mark ARABIC LETTER ALEF WITH WAVY HAMZA BELOW (U+0673) as a variant of
                        ARABIC LETTER ALEF WITH HAMZA BELOW (U+0625), but only when it appears in
                        its isolated or final forms: </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="0625">
        <var cp="0673" when="arabic-isolated"/>
        <var cp="0673" when="arabic-final"/>
    </char>
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>Only a single "when" or "not-when" attribute can be applied to any "var"
                        element, however, multiple "var" elements using the same mapping, but
                        different "when" or "not-when" attributes may be specified. If two
                        "when" attributes for the same "var" elements are different care must
                        be taken to ensure that they do not both match the same context; otherwise
                        the results are undefined.</t>
                    <t>Arabic is an example of a script for which such conditional variants
                        have been established in at least some existing LGRs.  The mechanism
                        defined here supports other forms of conditional variants that may
                        required by other scripts.</t>
                    <t>As described in <xref target="sequences"/> a "when" or "not-when" attribute
                        may also be specified to any "char" element in the data section to define
                        required or prohibited contextual conditions under which a code point is
                        valid. </t>
                </section>
                </section>

                <section title="Annotations">

                <t>Two attributes, the "ref" and "comment" attributes, can be used to annotate
                    individual elements in the LGR. They are ignored in machine-processing or
                    the LGR. The "ref" attribute is intended for formal annotations, and the
                    "comment" attribute for free form annotation. The latter can be applied
                    more widely.</t>

                <section title="The ref Attribute" anchor="ref">
                <t>Reference information may optionally be specified by a "ref" attribute, consisting of a space
                    delimited sequence of reference identifiers.
                </t>
                <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="522A" ref="0">
        <var cp="5220" ref="2 3"/>
        <var cp="5220" ref="2 3"/>
    </char>]]></artwork>
                </figure></t>
                <t>This facility is typically used to give source information for code points
                    or variant relations. This information is ignored when machine-processing an
                    LGR. If applied to a range the "ref" attribute applies to very code point
                    code point in the range. All reference identifiers MUST be from the set
                    declared in the "references" element (see <xref target="references"/>). It
                    is an error to repeat a reference identifier in the same "ref" attribute.
                    It is RECOMMENDED that identifiers be listed in ascending order. </t>
                <t>In addition to "char", "range" and "var" elements in the data section, a "ref"
                    attribute may be present for these elements that appear in the rules section
                    described below:  actions, literals ("char" inside a rule), as well as
                    for definitions of rules and classes, but not for named references using
                    the "by-ref" attribute defined below.  For these elements, the use of the
                    "by-ref" and "ref" attributes are mutually exclusive. None of the elements
                    in the metadata take a "ref" attribute; instead use the description
                    element there.</t>
                </section>

                <section title="The comment Attribute" anchor="comment">

                    <t>Any "char", "range" or "variant" element in the data section may contain an
                        optional "comment" attribute. The contents of a "comment" attribute are
                        free-form plain text. Comments are ignored in machine processing of the
                        table. Comment attributes may also be placed on all elements in the "rules"
                        section of the document, such as actions and match operators, such as
                        literals ("char"), as well as definitions of classes and rules, but not on
                        child elements of the "class" element. Finally, in the metadata, only the
                        "version" and "reference" elements may have "comment" attributes (to match the
                        syntax in <xref target="RFC3743"/>). </t>
                </section>

            </section>

            <section title="Code Point Tagging" anchor="tagging">
                <t>Typically, LGRs are used to explicitly designate allowable code points, where any
                    label that contains a code point not explicitly listed in the LGR is considered
                    an ineligible label according to the ruleset.
                </t>
                <t>For more complex registry rules, there may be a need to discern one or more
                    subsets of code points. This can be accomplished by applying an optional "tag"
                    attribute to "char" or "range" elements that are child elements of the "data"
                    element. By collecting code points that share the same tag value, character classes
                    may be defined (see <xref target="tag_based_classes" />) which can then be used
                    in whole label evaluation rules (see <xref target="match_operators" />).
                </t>
                <t>Each "tag" attribute may contain multiple values separated by white space. A tag
                    value is an identifier,  which may also include certain punctuation marks, such
                    as colon. Formally, it MUST correspond to the XML 1.0 Nmtoken (Name token)
                    production. It is an error to duplicate a value within the same "tag"
                    attribute. A "tag" attribute for a "range" element applies to all code points
                    in the range. Because code point sequences are not proper members of a set of
                    code points, a "tag" attribute MUST NOT be present in a "char" element defining
                    a code point sequence.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Whole Label and Context Evaluation">
            <section title="Basic Concepts">
                <t>The code points in a label sometimes need to satisfy context-based rules, for
                    example for the label to be considered valid, or to satisfy the context for a
                    variant mapping (see the description of the "when" attribute in <xref
                        target="parameterized_context_rule"/>). </t>
                <t>A Whole Label Evaluation rule (WLE) is applied to the whole label. It is used to
                    validate both original labels and variant labels computed from them using a
                    permutation over all applicable variant mappings. A conditional context rules is
                    a specialized form of WLE specific to the context around a single code point or
                    code point sequence. For example, if a rule is referenced in the "when"
                    attribute of a variant mapping it is used to describe the conditional context
                    under which the particular variant mapping is defined to exist. </t>

                <t>Each rule is defined in a "rule" element. A rule may contain the following as
                    child elements: </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>literal code points or code point sequences</t>
                        <t>character classes, which define sets of code points to be used for
                            context comparisons</t>
                        <t>context operators, which define when character classes and literals may
                            appear</t>
                        <t>nested rules, whether defined in place or invoked by reference</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t> Collectively, these are called match operators and are listed in <xref
                        target="match_operators"/>. </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Character Classes">
                <t>Character classes are sets of characters that often share a particular property.
                    While they function like sets in every way, even supporting the usual set
                    operators, they are called character classes here in a nod to the use of that
                    term in regular expression syntax. (This also avoids confusion with the term
                    "character set" in the sense of character encoding.)</t>

                <t>Character classes (or sets) can be specified in several ways: </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>by defining the set via matching a tag in the code point data. All
                            characters with the same "tag" attribute are part of the same class; </t>
                        <t>by referencing one of the Unicode character properties defined in the
                            Unicode Character Database <xref target="UAX42"/>; </t>
                        <t>by explicitly listing all the code points in the class; or</t>
                        <t>by defining the class as a set combination of any number of other
                            classes. </t>
                    </list>
                </t>

                <section title="Declaring and Invoking Named Classes" anchor="named_classes">
                <t>A character class has an optional "name" attribute, consisting of a single,
                    identifier not containing spaces. All names for classes must be unique.
                    If the "name" attribute is omitted, the class is anonymous and exists only
                    inside the rule or combined class where it is defined. A named character
                    class is defined independently and can be referenced by name from within
                    any rules or as part of other character class definitions.  </t>

                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <class name="example" comment="an example class definition">
        <char cp="0061" />
        <char cp="4E00" />
    </class>
    ...
    <rule>
        <class by-ref="example" />
    </rule>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t>An empty "class" element with a "by-ref" attribute is a reference to an
                    existing named class. The "by-ref" attribute cannot be used in the same
                    "class" element with any of these attributes: "name", "from-tag", "property"
                    or "ref". The "name" attribute MUST be present, if and only if the class is
                    a direct child element of the "rules" element.  It is an error to reference
                    a named class for which the definition has not been seen.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Tag-based Classes" anchor="tag_based_classes">
                    <t>The "char" or "range" elements that are child elements of the "data"
                        element may contain a "tag" attribute that consists of one or more
                        space separated tag values, for example:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="0061" tag="letter lower"/>
    <char cp="4E00" tag="letter"/>
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>This defines two tags for use with code point U+0061, the tag "letter" and
                        the tag "lower". Use</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <class name="letter" from-tag="letter">
    <class name="lower" from-tag="lower" />
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>

                    <t>to define two named character classes, "letter" and "lower", containing all
                        code points with the respective tags, the first with 0061 and 4E00 as
                        elements and the latter with 0061, but not 4E00 as an element. The "name"
                        attribute may be omitted for an anonymous in-place definition of a nested,
                        tag-based class.</t>
                    <t>Tag values are typically identifiers, with the addition of a few punctuation
                        symbols, such as colon. Formally they MUST correspond to the XML 1.0
                        Nmtoken (Name token) production. While a "tag" attribute may contain
                        a list of tag values, the "from-tag" attribute always contains a single tag
                        value.</t>

                    <t>If the document contains no "char" or "range" elements with a corresponding
                        tag, the character class represents the empty set. This is valid, to allow a
                        common "rules" element to be shared across files. However, it is RECOMMENDED
                        that implementations allow for a warning to ensure that referring to an
                        undefined tag in this way is intentional.</t>

                </section>

                <section title="Unicode Property-based Classes" anchor="property">
                    <t>A class is defined in terms of Unicode properties by giving the Unicode
                        property alias and the property value or property value alias, separated by
                        a colon. </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <class name="virama" property="ccc:9" />
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>The example above selects all code points for which the Unicode canonical
                        combining class (ccc) value is 9. This value of the ccc is assigned to all
                        code points that encode viramas. The string "ccc" is the short-alias for the
                        canonical combining class, as defined in the Unicode Character Database
                            <xref target="UAX42"/>.</t>
                    <t>Unicode properties may, in principle, change between versions of the Unicode
                        Standard. However, the values assigned for a given version are fixed. If
                        Unicode Properties are used, a Unicode version MUST be declared in the
                        "unicode-version" element in the header. (Note, some Unicode properties are
                        by definition stable across versions and do not change once assigned (see
                            <xref target="Unicode-Stability"/>.) </t>
                    <t>It is RECOMMENDED that all implementations processing LGR files provide support
                        for the following minimal set of Unicode properties:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>General Category (gc)</t>
                            <t>Script (sc)</t>
                            <t>Canonical Combining Class (ccc)</t>
                            <t>Bidi Class (bc)</t>
                            <t>Arabic Joining Type (jt)</t>
                            <t>Indic Syllabic Category (InSC)</t>
                            <t>Deprecated (Dep)</t>
                        </list>
                        The short name for each property is given in parentheses.</t>
                    <t>If a program that is using an LGR to determine the validity of a label
                        encounters a property that it does not support, it MUST abort with an
                        error.</t>
                </section>

                <section title="Explicitly Declared Classes">

                    <t>A class of code points may also be declared by listing the code points
                        that are a member of the class. This is useful when tagging cannot be
                        used because code points are not listed individually as part of the
                        eligible set of code points for the given LGR, for example because
                        they only occur in code point sequences.
                    </t>
                    <t>To define a class in terms of an explicit list of code points use a
                        space separated list of hexadecimal code point values:</t>
                    <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[     <class name="abcd">0061 0062 0063 0064</class>]]></artwork>
                    </figure></t>
                    <t>This defines a class named "abcd" containing the code points for
                        characters "a", "b", "c" and "d". The ordering of the code points
                        is not material, but it is RECOMMENDED to list them in ascending
                        order.
                    </t>
                    <t>Code point ranges are represented by a start and end value separated
                        by a hyphen. The following declaration is equivalent to the preceding:
                    </t>
                    <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <class name="abcd">0061-0064</class>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure></t>
                    <t>Range and code point declarations can be freely intermixed:</t>
                    <t><figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <class name="abcd">0061 0062-0063 0064</class>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure></t>
                </section>

                <section title="Combined Classes" anchor="combined_classes">
                    <t>Classes may be combined using operators for set complement, union,
                        intersection, difference and symmetric difference (exclusive-or). Because
                        classes fundamentally function like sets, the union of several character
                        classes is itself a class, for example. </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure title="Set Operators">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
+-------------------+----------------------------------------------+
| Logical Operation | Example                                      |
+-------------------+----------------------------------------------+
| Complement        | <complement><class by-ref="xxx"></complement>|
+-------------------+----------------------------------------------+
| Union             | <union>                                      |
|                   |    <class by-ref="class-1"/>                 |
|                   |    <class by-ref="class-2"/>                 |
|                   |    <class by-ref="class-3"/>                 |
|                   | </union>                                     |
+-------------------+----------------------------------------------+
| Intersection      | <intersection>                               |
|                   |    <class by-ref="class-1"/>                 |
|                   |    <class by-ref="class-2"/>                 |
|                   | </intersection>                              |
+-------------------+----------------------------------------------+
| Difference        | <difference>                                 |
|                   |    <class by-ref="class-1"/>                 |
|                   |    <class by-ref="class-2"/>                 |
|                   | </difference>                                |
+-------------------+----------------------------------------------+
| Symmetric         | <symmetric-difference>                       |
| Difference        |    <class by-ref="class-1"/>                 |
|                   |    <class by-ref="class-2"/>                 |
|                   | </symmetric-difference>                      |
+-------------------+----------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>

                    <t>The elements from this table may be arbitrarily nested inside each other,
                        subject to the following restriction: a "complement" element MUST contain
                        precisely one "class" or one of the operator elements, while an
                        "intersection", "symmetric-difference" or "difference" element MUST contain
                        precisely two, and a "union" element MUST contain two or more of these
                        elements. </t>

                    <t>An anonymous combined class can be defined directly inside a rule or of the
                        match operator elements that allow child elements (see <xref
                            target="match_operators"/>) by using the set combination as the outer
                        element. </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <rule>
        <union>
            <class by-ref="xxx"/>
            <class by-ref="yyy"/>
        </union>
    </rule>
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>The example shows the definition of an anonymous combined class that
                        represents the union of classes "xxx" and "yyy". There is no need to wrap
                        this union inside another "class" element, and, in fact, set combination
                        elements MUST NOT be nested inside a "class" element. </t>
                    <t>Lastly, to create a named combined class that can be referenced in other
                        classes or in rules as &lt;class by-ref="xxxyyy"/&gt;, add a "name"
                        attribute to the set combination element, for example &lt;union
                        name="xxxyyy" /&gt; and place it at the top level immediately below
                        the "rules" element (see <xref target="named_classes" />.</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[ <rules>
    <union class name="xxxyyy">
        <class by-ref="xxx"/>
        <class by-ref="yyy"/>
    </union>
      . . .
  </ rules>    
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>Because (as for ordinary sets) a combination of classes is itself a
                        class, no matter by what combinations of set operators a combined class
                        is created, a reference to it always uses the "class" element as
                        described in <xref target="named_classes" />. That is, a named class
                        is always referenced via an empty "class" element using the "by-ref"
                        attribute containing the name of the class to be referenced. </t>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section title="Whole Label and Context Rules">
                <t>Each rule is comprised of a series of matching operators that must be satisfied
                    in order to determine whether a label meets a given condition. Rules may
                    reference other rules or character classes defined elsewhere in the table. </t>

                <section title="The rule Element" anchor="rule">
                    <t>A matching rule is defined by a "rule" element, the child elements of which
                        are one of the match operators from <xref target="match_operators" />.
                        In evaluating a rule, each child element is matched in order. Rule elements
                        may be nested.</t>
                    <t>Rules may optionally be named using a "name" attribute containing a single
                        identifier string with no spaces. A named rule may be incorporated into
                        another rule by reference. If the "name" attribute is omitted, the rule is
                        anonymous and may not be incorporated by reference into another rule or
                        referenced by an action or "when" attribute. </t>

                    <t>A simple rule to match a label where all characters are members of the class
                        "preferred":</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <rule name="preferred">
        <start />
        <class by-ref="preferred" count="1+"/>
        <end />
    </rule>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>Rules are paired with explicit and implied actions, triggering these actions
                        when a rule matches a label. For example, a simple explicit action for the
                        rule shown above would be: </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <action disp="allocate" match="preferred" />]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>which has the effect of setting the policy disposition for a label made up
                        entirely of "preferred" code points to "allocate". Explicit actions are
                        further discussed in <xref target="actions"/> and the use of rules in
                        conditional contexts for implied actions is discussed in <xref target="when"
                        /> and <xref target="implied_actions"/>. </t>
                </section>
                <section title="The Match Operators" anchor="match_operators">
                    <t>The child elements of a rule are a series of match operators, which are
                        listed here by type and name and with a basic example or two.</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure title="Match Operators">
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
+------------+-------------+------------------------------------+
| Type       | Operator    | Examples                           |
+------------+-------------+------------------------------------+
| logical    | any         | <any />                            |
|            +-------------+------------------------------------+
|            | choice      | <choice>                           |
|            |             |  <rule by-ref="alternative1"/>     |
|            |             |  <rule by-ref="alternative2"/>     |
|            |             | </choice>                          |
+--------------------------+------------------------------------+
| positional | start       | <start />                          |
|            +-------------+------------------------------------+
|            | end         | <end />                            |
+--------------------------+------------------------------------+
| literal    | char        | <char cp="0061 0062 0063" />       |
+--------------------------+------------------------------------+
| set        | class       | <class by-ref="class1" />          |
|            |             | <class>0061 0064-0065</class>      |
+--------------------------+------------------------------------+
| group      | rule        | <rule by-ref="rule1" />            |
|            |             | <rule><any /><rule />              |
+--------------------------+------------------------------------+
| contextual | anchor      | <anchor />                         |
|            +-------------+------------------------------------+
|            | look-ahead  | <look-ahead><any /></look-ahead>   |
|            +-------------+------------------------------------+
|            | look-behind | <look-behind><any /></look-behind> |
+--------------------------+------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>Any element defining an anonymous class can be used as a match operator,
                        including any of the set combination operators (see <xref
                            target="combined_classes"/>) as well as references to a named
                        classes.</t>

                    <t>All match operators shown as empty elements in the Examples column of the
                        table above do not support child elements of their own; otherwise match
                        operators may be nested. In particular, anonymous "rule" elements can be used
                        for grouping.</t>
                </section>

                <section title="The count Attribute">

                    <t>The optional "count" attribute specifies the minimally required or maximal
                        permitted number of times a match operator is used to match input. If the
                        "count" attribute is
                        <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                            <t hangText="n"> the match operator matches the input exactly n
                                times, where n is 1 or greater. </t>
                            <t hangText="n+"> the match operator matches the input at least n times,
                                where n is 0 or greater. </t>
                            <t hangText="n:m"> the match operator matches the input at least n times
                                where n is 0 or greater, but matches the input up to m times in
                                total, where m > n. If m = n and n > 0, the match operator matches
                                the input exactly n times. </t>
                        </list>
                        If there is no "count" attribute, the match operator matches the input
                        exactly once.</t>
                    <t>In matching, greedy evaluation is used in the sense defined for
                        regular expressions: beyond the required number or times, the input is
                        matched as many times as possible, but not so often as to prevent a match of
                        the remainder of the rule. </t>

                    <t>The "count" attribute MUST NOT be applied to match operators of type "start",
                        "end", "anchor", "look-ahead" and "look-behind" or to any operators, such as
                        "rule" or "choice" that contain them, whether the latter are declared in
                        place or used by reference. The "count" attribute may be applied to "class"
                        and "rule" elements only if they do not have a "name" attribute, that is, to
                        anonymous rules and classes or any invocation of predefined rules or classes
                        by reference. </t>
                    <t>The optional "count" attribute MAY be applied to match operators of type "any",
                        "char" and "class", as well as to match operators "choice" and "rule", as
                        long as they contain none of the operators "start", "end", "anchor",
                        "look-ahead" and "look-behind" as direct or indirect child elements. The
                        same requirement applies recursively to any "rule" element referenced inside
                        a "choice" or "rule" with a "count" attribute. The "count" attribute cannot
                        appear in the same element as a "name" attribute.</t>
                </section>

                <section title="The name and by-ref Attributes">
                        <t>Like classes (see <xref target="named_classes" />), rules declared as
                            immediate child elements of the "rules" element MUST be named
                            using a unique "name" attribute, and all other instances MUST NOT be
                            named. Anonymous rules and classes or reference to named rules and
                            classes can be nested inside other match operators by reference.</t>
                        <t>To reference a named rule or class inside a rule or match operator
                            use a rule or "class" element with an optional "by-ref" attribute
                            containing the name of the referenced element. It is an error to
                            reference a rule or class for which the definition has not been
                            seen. The "by-ref" attribute cannot appear in the same element as
                            the "name" attribute, or in an element that has any child elements.</t>
                        <t>Here's an example of a rule requiring that all labels be letters
                            (optionally followed by combining marks) and possibly digits. The
                            example shows rules and classes referenced by name.</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <class name="letter" property="gc:L"/>
    <class name="combining-mark" property="gc:M"/>
    <class name="digit" property="gc:Nd">
    <rule name="letter-grapheme">
       <class by-ref="letter" count="1+"/>
       <class by-ref="combining-mark" count="0+"/>
    </rule>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="The choice Element">

                    <t>The "choice" element is used to represent a list of two or more
                        alternatives:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <rule name="ldh">
       <choice count="1+">
           <class by-ref="letters"/>
           <class by-ref="digits"/>
           <char cp="002D" comment="literal HYPHEN"/>
       </choice>
    </rule>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>Each child element of a "choice" represents one alternative. The first
                        matching alternative determines the match for the "choice" element. To express
                        a choice where an alternative itself consists of a sequence of elements,
                        the sequence must be wrapped in an anonymous rule. </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Literal Code Point Sequences">

                    <t>A literal code point sequence matches a single code point or a sequence. It
                        is defined by a "char" element, with the code point or sequence to be
                        matched given by the "cp" attribute. When used as a literal, a "char"
                        element may contain a "count" in addition to the "cp" attribute and optional
                        "comment" or "ref" attributes. No other attributes or child elements are
                        permitted. </t>
                </section>

                <section title="The any Element">

                    <t>The "any" element matches any single code point. It may have a "count"
                        attribute. For an example see <xref target="IDNA2008-example"/>
                    </t>
                    <t>Unlike a literal, the "any" element" may not have a "ref" attribute.</t>
                </section>

                <section title="The start and end Elements">

                    <t>To match the beginning or end of a label, use the "start" or "end"
                        element. An empty label would match this rule:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <rule name="empty-label">
        <start/>
        <end/>
    </rule>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>Conceptually, Whole Label Evaluation Rules evaluate the label as a whole,
                        but in practice,  many rules do not actually need to be specified to match
                        the entire label. For example, to express a requirement of not starting a
                        label with a digit, a rule needs to describe only the initial part of a
                        label.</t>
                    <t>This example uses the previously defined rules, together with start and end tag, to define
                        a rule that requires that an entire label is well-formed. For this example
                        that means, that it must start with a letter and contains no leading digits
                        or combining marks, nor combining marks placed on digits.</t>
                    <t><figure><artwork><![CDATA[     <rule name="leading-letter" >
       <start />
       <rule by-ref="letter-grapheme" count="1"/>
       <choice count="0+">
         <rule by-ref="letter-grapheme" count="0+"/>
         <class by-ref="digit" count="0+"/>
       </choice>
       <end />
     </rule>]]>
                    </artwork></figure></t>

                    <t>Each "start" or "end" element occurs at most once in a rule, except if nested
                        inside a "choice" element in such a way that in matching each alternative
                        at most one occurrence of each is encountered. Otherwise, the result is an
                        error; as is any case where a "start" or "end" element is not encountered as
                        first or last element to be matched	, respectively, in matching a rule. Start
                        and end elements do not have a "count" or any other attribute. It is an error
                        for any match operator enclosing a nested "start" or "end" element to have a
                        "count" attribute.</t>

                </section>

                <section title="Example rule from IDNA2008" anchor="IDNA2008-example">

                    <t>This is an example of the whole label evaluation rule from <xref
                            target="RFC5892"/> forbidding the mixture of the Arabic-Indic and
                        extended Arabic-Indic digits in the same label. The example also
                        demonstrates several instances of the use of anonymous rules for
                        grouping.</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <data>
       <range first-cp="0660" last-cp="0669" not-when="mixed-digits"
              tag="arabic-indic-digits" />
       <range first-cp="06F0" last-cp="06F9" not-when="mixed-digits"
              tag="extended-arabic-indic-digits" />
    </data>
    <rules>
       <rule name="mixed-digits">
          <choice>
            <rule>
                <class from-tag="arabic-indic-digits"/>
                <any count="0+"/>
                <class from-tag="extended-arabic-indic-digits"/>
             </rule>
             <rule>
                <class from-tag="extended-arabic-indic-digits"/>
                <any count="0+"/>
                <class from-tag="arabic-indic-digits"/>
             </rule>
          </choice>
       </rule>
    </rules>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>The effect of this example is that a label containing a code point
                        from either of the two digit ranges is invalid for any label matching
                        the "mixed-digits" rule, that is, anytime a code point from the other
                        range is also present. Note that this is not the same as invalidating
                        the definition of the "range" elements.</t>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="parameterized_context_rule" title="Parameterized Context or When Rules">
                <t>A special type of rule provides a context for evaluating the validity of a code
                    point or variant mapping. This rule is invoked by the "when" attribute described
                    in <xref target="when"/>. An action implied by a context rule always has a
                    disposition of "invalid" whenever the rule is not matched (see <xref
                        target="implied_actions"/>). Conversely, a "not-when" attribute results in a
                    disposition of invalid whenever the rule is matched.</t>

                <section title="The anchor Element">

                    <t>Such parameterized context or "When Rules" may contain a special place holder
                        represented by an "anchor" element. As each When Rule is evaluated, the
                        "anchor" element is replaced by a literal corresponding to the "cp"
                        attribute of the element containing the "when" (or "not-when") attribute.
                        The match to the "anchor" element must be at the same position in the label
                        as the code point or variant mapping triggering the When Rule. </t>
                    <t>For example, the Greek lower numeral sign is invalid if not immediately
                        preceding a character in the Greek script. This is most naturally addressed
                        with a When Rule using look-ahead: </t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="0375" when="preceding-greek"/>
    ...
    <class name="greek-script" property="sc:Grek"/>
    <rule name="preceding-greek">
        <anchor/>
        <look-ahead>
            <class by-ref="greek-script"/>
        </look-ahead>
    </rule>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>In evaluating this rule, the "anchor" element is treated as if it was
                        replaced by a literal</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="0375"/>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>but only the instance of U+0375 at the given position is evaluated. If a
                        label had two instances of U+0375 with the first one matching the rule and
                        the second not, then evaluating the When Rule MUST succeed for the first and
                        fail for the second instance. </t>
                    <t>Unlike other rules, When Rules containing an "anchor" element MUST only be
                        invoked via the "when" or "not-when" attributes on code points or variants;
                        otherwise their "anchor" elements cannot be evaluated. However, it is
                        possible to invoke rules not containing an "anchor" element from a "when" or
                        "not-when" attribute. (See <xref target="omitting"/>) </t>

                </section>

                <section title="The look-behind and look-ahead Elements">

                    <t>Context rules use the "look-behind" and "look-ahead" elements to define
                        context before and after the code point sequence matched by the "anchor"
                        element. If the "anchor" element is omitted, neither the "look-behind" nor
                        the "look-ahead" element may be present. </t>
                    <t>Here is an example of a rule that defines an "initial" context for an Arabic
                        code point:</t>
                    <t>
                        <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[    <class name="transparent" property="jt:T"/>
    <class name="right-joining" property="jt:R"/>
    <class name="left-joining" property="jt:L"/>
    <class name="dual-joining" property="jt:D"/>
    <class name="non-joining" property="jt:U"/>
    <rule name="Arabic-initial">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <start/>
          <rule>
            <class by-ref="transparent" count="0+"/>
            <class by-ref="non-joining"/>
          </rule>
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor/>
      <look-ahead>
        <class by-ref="transparent" count="0+" />
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="right-joining" />
          <class by-ref="dual-joining" />
        </choice>
      </look-ahead>
    </rule>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </t>
                    <t>A "when rule" contains any combination of "look-behind", "anchor" and
                        "look-ahead" elements in that order. Each of these elements occurs at most
                        once, except if nested inside a "choice" element in such a way that in
                        matching each alternative at most one occurrence of each is encountered.
                        Otherwise, the result is undefined. None of these elements takes a "count"
                        attribute, nor does any enclosing match operator. Otherwise, the result is
                        undefined. If a context rule contains a "look-ahead" or "look-behind" element,
                        it MUST contain an "anchor" element. If, because of a choice element, a
                        required anchor is not actually encountered, the results are undefined. </t>
                </section>

                <section title="Omitting the anchor Element" anchor="omitting">

                    <t> If the "anchor" element is omitted, the evaluation of the context rule is
                        not tied to the position of the code point or sequence associated with the
                        "when" attribute. </t>
                    <t>According to <xref target="RFC5892"/> Katakana middle dot is invalid in any
                        label not containing at least one Japanese character anywhere in the label.
                        Because this requirement is independent of the position of the middle dot,
                        the rule does not require an "anchor" element.</t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="30FB" when="japanese-in-label"/>
    <rule name="japanese-in-label">
        <union>
            <class property="sc:Hani"/>
            <class property="sc:Kata"/>
            <class property="sc:Hira"/>
        </union>
    </rule>]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>The Katakana middle dot is used only with Han, Katakana or Hiragana. The
                        corresponding When Rule requires that at least one code point in the label
                        is in one of these scripts, but the position of that code point is
                        independent of the location of the middle dot and no anchor therefore
                        required. (Note that the Katakana middle dot itself is of script Common).
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="The action Element" anchor="actions">

            <t>The purpose of a rule is to trigger a specific action. Often, the action simply
                results in blocking or invalidating a label that does not match a rule. An example
                of an action invalidating a label because it does not match a rule named
                "leading-letter" is as follows: </t>
            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[   <action disp="invalid" not-match="leading-letter"/>]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>

            <t>If an action is to be triggered on matching a rule, a "match" attribute is used
                instead. Actions are evaluated in the order that they appear in the XML file, Once
                an action is triggered by a label, the disposition defined in the "disp" attribute
                is assigned to the label and no other actions are evaluated for that label. </t>

            <t>The goal of the Label Generation Rules is to identify all labels and variant labels
                and to assign them disposition values. These dispositions are then fed into a further
                process that ultimately implements all aspects of policy. To allow this specification
                to be used with the widest range of policies, the permissible values for the "disp"
                attribute are neither defined nor restricted. Nevertheless a set of commonly used
                disposition values is RECOMMENDED. (See
                <xref target="recommended_disposition_values" />)</t>

            <section title="The match and not-match Attributes" anchor="match_attribute">
                <t>A "match" or "not-match" attribute specify a rule that must be matched or not
                    matched as a condition for triggering an action. Only a single rule may be named
                    as the value of a "match" or "not-match" attribute. Because rules may be
                    composed of other rules, this restriction to a single attribute value does not
                    impose any limitation on the contexts that can trigger an action.</t>

                <t>An action may contain a "match" or a "not-match" attribute, but not both. An
                    action without any attributes is triggered by all labels unconditionally. For a
                    very simple LGR, the following action would allocate all labels that match the
                    repertoire:</t>

                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <action disp="allocate" />]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>

                <t>Since rules are evaluated for all labels, whether they are the original label or
                    computed by permuting the defined and valid variant mappings for the label's
                    code points, actions based on matching or not matching a rule may be triggered
                    for both original and variant labels, but they the rules are not affected by the
                    disposition attributes of the variant mappings. To trigger any actions base on
                    these dispositions requires the use additional optional attributes for actions
                    described next. </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Actions with Variant Type Triggers" anchor="variants_actions">
                <section title="The all-, any- and only-variants Attributes" anchor="variant_triggers">
                    <t>An action may contain one of the optional attributes "any-variant",
                        "all-variants", or "only-variants" defining triggers based on variant
                        types. The permitted value for these attributes consists of one or
                        more variant type values, separated by spaces. When a variant label is
                        generated, these variant type values are compared to the set of type values
                        on the variant mappings used to generate the particular variant label
                        (see <xref target="processing" />).</t>

                    <t>Any single match may trigger an action that contains an "any-variant"
                        attribute, while for an "all-variants" or "only-variants" attribute,
                        the variant type for all variant code points must match one or several
                        of the types values specified in to trigger the action. An
                        "only-variants" attribute will trigger the action only if all code
                        points of the variant label have variant mappings from the original code
                        points. In other words, the label contains no original code points other
                        than those with a reflexive mapping (see <xref
                                target="reflexive_mapping" />).</t>

                    <t><figure><artwork><![CDATA[     <char cp="0078" comment="x" />
        <var cp="0078" type="allocate" comment="reflexive" />
        <var cp="0079" type="block" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0079"  comment="y"/>
        <var cp="0078" type="allocate" />
    </char>
    . . .
    <action disp="block" any-variants="block" />
    <action disp="allocate" only-variants="allocate" />
    <action disp="some-type" any-variants="allocate" />	]]></artwork></figure></t>
                    <t>In the example above, the label "xx" would have variant labels "xx", "xy",
                        "yx" and "yy". The first action would result in blocking any variant label
                        containing "y", because the variant mapping from "x" to "y" is of type
                        "block", triggering the "any-variants" condition. Because in this example
                        "x" has a reflexive variant mapping to itself of type "allocate" the
                        original label "xx" has a reflexive variant "xx" that would trigger the
                        "only_variants" condition on the second action. </t>

                    <t>A label "yy" would have the variants "xy", "yx" and "xx". Because the variant
                        mapping from "y" to "x" is of type "allocate" and a mapping from "y" to
                        "y" is not defined, the labels "xy" and "yx" trigger the "any-variants"
                        condition on the third label.  The variant "xx", being generated using the
                        mapping from "y" to "x" of type "allocate", would trigger the "only-variants"
                        condition on the section action. As there is no reflexive variant "yy", the
                        original label "yy" cannot trigger any variant type triggers. However, it
                        could still trigger an action defined as matching or not matching a rule.</t>

                    <t>In each action, one variant type trigger may be present by itself or in
                        conjunction with an attribute matching or not-matching a rule. If variant
                        triggers and rule-matching triggers are used together, the label MUST "match"
                        or respectively "not-match" the specified rule, AND satisfy the conditions
                        on the variant type values given by the "any-variant", "all-variants", or
                        "only-variants" attribute.</t>
                </section>

                <section title="Example from RFC 3743 Tables" anchor="rfc3743_example">
                    <t>This section gives an example of using variant type triggers, combined with
                        variants with reflexive mappings (<xref target="reflexive_mapping"/>) to
                        achieve LGRs that implement tables like those defined according to <xref
                                target="RFC3743"/> where the goal is to allow only variants that
                        consist entirely of simplified or traditional variants, in addition to the
                        original label. </t>
                 <t>Assuming an LGR where all variants have been given suitable "type" attributes
                     of "block", "simplified", "traditional", or "both", similar to the ones
                     discussed in <xref target="translate_rfc3743" />. Given such an LGR, the
                     following example actions evaluate the disposition for the variant label:
                </t>
                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <action disp="block" any-variant="block" />
    <action disp="allocate" only-variants="simplified both" />
    <action disp="allocate" only-variants="traditional both" />
    <action disp="block" all-variants="simplified traditional " />
    <action disp="allocate" />]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
                <t>The first action matches any variant label for which at least one of the code
                    point variants is of type "block". The second matches any variant label for
                    which all of the code point  variants are of type "simplified" or "both",
                    in other words an all-simplified label. The third matches any label for which
                    all variants are of type "traditional" or "both", that is all traditional. These
                    two actions are not triggered by any variant labels containing some original
                    code points, unless each of those code points has a variant defined with
                    a reflexive mapping (<xref target="reflexive_mapping" />). </t>

                <t>The final two actions rely on the fact that actions are evaluated in sequence,
                    and that the first action triggered also defines the final disposition for a
                    variant label (see <xref target="precedence"/>). They further rely on the
                    assumption that the only variants with type "both" are also reflexive
                    variants.</t>
                <t>Given these assumptions, any remaining simplified or traditional variants must
                    then be part of a mixed label, and so are blocked; all labels surviving to the
                    last action are original code points only (that is the original label). The
                    example assumes that an original label may be a mixed label; if that is not
                    the case, the disposition for the last action would be set to "block".</t>

                <t>There are exceptions where the assumption on reflexive mappings made above does
                    not hold, so this basic scheme needs some refinements to cover all cases. For
                    a more complete example, see <xref target="translate_rfc3743" />.</t>
                </section>

            </section>
            <section title="Recommended Disposition Values" anchor="recommended_disposition_values">
                <t>The precise nature of the policy action taken in response to a disposition and
                    the name of the corresponding "disp" attributes are only partially defined here.
                    It is strongly RECOMMENDED to use the following dispositions only with their
                    conventional sense. </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="invalid">The resulting string is not a valid label. This
                            disposition may be assigned implicitly, see <xref
                                target="implied_actions"/>. No variant labels should be generated
                            from a variant mapping with this type. </t>
                        <t hangText="block">The resulting string is a valid label, but should be
                            block from registration. This would typically apply for a derived
                            variant that has is undesirable as having no practical use or being
                            confusingly similar to some other label. </t>
                        <t hangText="allocate">The resulting string should be reserved for use by
                            the same operator of the origin string, but not automatically allocated
                            for use. </t>
                        <t hangText="activate">The resulting string should be activated for use.
                            (This is the typical default action if no dispositions are defined and
                            is known as a "preferred" variant in <xref target="RFC3743"/>) </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Precedence" anchor="precedence">
                <t>Actions are applied in the order of their appearance in the file. This defines
                    their relative precedence. The first action triggered by a label defines the
                    disposition for that label. To define a specific order of precedence list the
                    actions in the desired order. The conventional order of precedence for the
                    actions defined in <xref target="recommended_disposition_values"/> is "invalid",
                    "block", "allocate", then "activate". This default precedence is used for the
                    default actions defined in <xref target="default_actions"/>. </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Implied Actions" anchor="implied_actions">
                <t>The context rules on code points ("not-when" or "when" rules) carry an implied
                    action with a disposition of "invalid" (not eligible). These rules are
                    evaluated at the time the code points for a label or its variant labels are
                    checked for validity (see <xref target="processing"/>). In other words, they
                    are evaluated before any of the whole-label evaluation rules and with higher
                    precedence. The context rules for variant mappings are evaluated when variants
                    are generated and/or when variant tables are made symmetric and transitive.
                    They have an implied action with a disposition of "invalid" which means a
                    putative variant mapping does not exist whenever the given context matches a
                    "not-when" rule or fails to match a "when" rule specified for that mapping.
                    The result of that disposition is that the variant mapping is ignored in
                    generating variant labels and the value is therefore not accessible to trigger
                    any explicit actions.</t>
                <t>Note that such non-existing variant mapping is different from a blocked variant,
                    which is a variant code point mapping that exists but results in a label that
                    may not be allocated. </t>

            </section>
            <section title="Default Actions" anchor="default_actions">

                <t>As described in <xref target="actions"/> any variant mapping may be given a
                    "type" attribute. An action containing an "any-variant"
                    or "all-variants" attribute relates these type values to a resulting
                    disposition for the entire variant label. </t>

                <t>If no actions are defined for the standard disposition values of "invalid",
                    "block", "allocate" and "activate", then the following default actions exist
                    that are shown below in their default order of precedence (see <xref
                        target="precedence"/>). This default order for evaluating dispositions
                    applies only to labels that triggered no explicitly defined actions and which
                    are therefore handled by default actions. Default actions have a lower order of
                    precedence than explicit actions (see <xref target="determining_dispositions"
                    />). </t>
                <t>The default actions for variant labels are defined as follows:</t>

                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <action disp="invalid" any-variant="invalid"/>
    <action disp="block" any-variant="block"/>
    <action disp="allocate" any-variant="allocate"/>
    <action disp="activate" all-variants="activate"/>]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>

                <t>A final default action sets the disposition to "allocate" for any label matching
                    the repertoire for which no other action has been triggered (catch-all). </t>
                <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[    <action disp="allocate" />]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Processing a Label Against an LGR" anchor="processing">

            <section title="Determining Eligibility for a Label">

                <t>In order to test a specific label for membership in the LGR, a consumer of the
                    LGR must iterate through each code point within a given label, and test that
                    each code point is a member of the LGR. If any code point is not a member of
                    the LGR, the label shall be deemed as invalid.</t>

                <t>An individual code point is deemed a member of the LGR when it is listed using
                    a "char" element, or is part of a range defined with a "range" element, and all
                    necessary condition in any "when" or "not-when" attributes are correctly
                    satisfied.</t>

                <t>Alternatively, a code point is also deemed a member of the LGR when it forms
                    part of a sequence that corresponds to a sequence listed using a "char"
                    element for which the "cp" attribute defines a sequence, and all necessary
                    condition in any "when" or "not-when" attributes are correctly satisfied.</t>

                <t>A label must also not trigger any action that results in a disposition of
                    "invalid", otherwise it is deemed not eligible. (This step may need to be
                    deferred, until variant code point dispositions have been determined).</t>

                <t>For LGRs that contain reflexive variant mappings (defined in
                    <xref target="reflexive_mapping" />), the final evaluation of eligibility for
                    the label must be deferred until variants are generated. In essence, LGRs that
                    use this feature treat the original label as the (identity) variant of itself.
                    For such LGRs, the ordinary iteration over code points would generally only
                    exclude a subset of invalid labels, but it could be used effectively as a
                    pre-screening.</t>

            </section>

            <section title="Determining Variants for a Label">

                <t>For a given eligible label, the set of variant labels is deemed to consist of
                    each possible permutation of original code points and substituted code points
                    or sequences defined in "var" elements, whereby all "when" and "not-when"
                    attributes are correctly satisfied for each "char" or "var" element in the
                    given permutation and all applicable whole label evaluation rules are satisfied
                    as follows:

                    <list style="numbers">

                        <t>Create each possible permutation of a label, by substituting each code
                            point or code point sequence in turn by any defined variant mapping
                            (including any reflexive mappings)</t>

                        <t>Apply variant mappings with "when" or "not-when" attributes only if
                            the conditions are satisfied; otherwise they are not defined</t>

                        <t>Record each of the "type" values on the variant mappings used in
                            creating a given variant label in a disposition set; for any unmapped
                            code point record the "type" value of any reflexive variant (see
                            <xref target="reflexive_mapping" />)</t>

                        <t>Determine the disposition for each variant label per <xref
                                target="determining_dispositions" /></t>

                        <t>If the disposition is "invalid", remove the label from the set</t>

                        <t>If final evaluation of the disposition for the unpermuted label per
                            <xref target="determining_dispositions" /> results in a disposition
                            of "invalid", remove all associated variant labels from the set.</t>

                    </list>
                </t>

            </section>

            <section title="Determining a Disposition for a Label or Variant Label"
                     anchor="determining_dispositions">

                <t>For a given label (variant or original), its disposition is determined by
                    evaluating in order of their appearance all actions for which the label or
                    variant label satisfies the conditions.

                    <list style="numbers">

                        <t>For any label, the disposition is given by the value of the "disp"
                            attribute for the first action triggered by the label. An action is
                            triggered, if any of the following is true:

                        <list style="symbols">

                            <t>the label matches or doesn't match the whole label evaluation
                                rule, given in the "match" or "not-match" attribute respectively
                                for that action;</t>

                            <t>any or all of the recorded variant types for a variant label match
                                the types specified in an "any-variant", "all-variants", or
                                "only-variants" attribute, for that action, and in case of
                                "only-variants", the label contains only code points that are the
                                target of applied variant mappings;</t>

                            <t>the label matches or doesn't match the whole label evaluation rule,
                                given in the "match" or "not-match" attribute respectively for that
                                action and any or all of the recorded variant types for a variant
                                label match the types specified in an "any-variant", "all-variants",
                                or "only-variants" attribute, respectively, for that action, and in
                                case of "only-variants" the label contains only code points that
                                are the target of applied variant mappings; or</t>

                            <t>the action does not contain any "match", "not-match", "any-variant"
                                or "all-variants" attributes: catch-all.</t>

                        </list>
                        </t>

                        <t>For any remaining variant label, assign the variant label the disposition
                            using the default actions defined in <xref target="default_actions" />.
                            For this step, variant types outside the predefined recommended set
                            (see <xref target="recommended_disposition_values" />) are ignored.
                        </t>

                        <t>For any remaining label, set the disposition to "allocate". </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>


        </section>

        <section title="Conversion to and from Other Formats">

            <t>Both <xref target="RFC3743"/> and <xref target="RFC4290"/> provide different grammars
                for IDN tables. These formats are unable to fully cater for the increased
                requirements of contemporary IDN variant policies. </t>

            <t>This specification is a superset of functionality provided by these IDN table
                formats, thus any table expressed in those formats can be expressed in this format.
                Automated conversion can be conducted between tables conformant with the grammar
                specified in each document. </t>
            <t>For notes on how to translate an RFC 3743-style table, see <xref
                    target="translate_rfc3743"/>.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>This document does not specify any IANA actions.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>If a system that is querying an identifier list (such as a domain zone) that uses
                the rules in this memo, and those rules are not implemented correctly, and that
                system is relying on the rules being applied, the system might fail if the rules
                are not applied in a predictable fashion. This could cause security problems for
                the querying system.</t>
        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>
        <references> &rfc3339; &rfc3743; &rfc4290; &rfc5646; &rfc5564; &rfc5892; <reference
                anchor="Unicode-Stability">
                <front>
                    <title>Unicode Encoding Stability Policy, Property Value Stability</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="Unicode">Unicode Consortium</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
                <format type="HTML"
                    target="http://www.unicode.org/policies/stability_policy.html#Property_Value"/>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="Unicode-Versions">
                <front>
                    <title>Unicode Version Numbering</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="Unicode">Unicode Consortium</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
                <format type="HTML" target="http://unicode.org/versions/#Version_Numbering"/>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="UAX42">
                <front>
                    <title>Unicode Character Database in XML</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="Unicode">Unicode Consortium</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
                <format type="HTML" target="http://unicode.org/reports/tr42/"/>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="LGR-PROCEDURE">
                <front>
                    <title>Procedure to Develop and Maintain the Label Generation Rules for the Root
                        Zone in Respect of IDNA Labels </title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
                            Numbers</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/><!--    March, 2013</date> -->
                </front>
                <format type="PDF"
                    target="http://www.icann.org/en/resources/idn/draft-lgr-procedure-07dec12-en.pdf"
                />
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="TDIL-HINDI">
                <front>
                    <title>Devanagari Script Behaviour for Hindi </title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="TDIL">Technology Development for Indian Languages
                            (TDIL) Programme</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/><!-- October 2013</date> -->
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="XML">
                <front>
                    <title>Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization abbrev="W3C">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/>
                </front>
                <format type="HTML" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/"/>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="ASIA-TABLE">
                <front>
                    <title>.ASIA ZH IDN Language Table</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>DotAsia Organisation</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date/><!-- March, 2011 -->
                </front>
            </reference>
        </references>

        <section title="Example Tables">
            <t>The following presents a minimal LGR table defining the lower case LDH
                (letter-digit-hyphen) repertoire and containing no rules or metadata elements.
                Many simple LGR tables will look quite similar, except that they would contain some
                metadata.</t>
            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
&lt;lgr xmlns="http://www.iana.org/lgr/0.1"&gt;
&lt;data&gt;
    &lt;char cp="002D" comment="HYPHEN (-)" /&gt;
    &lt;range first-cp="0030" last-cp="0039"
      comment="DIGIT ZERO - DIGIT NINE" /&gt;
    &lt;range first-cp="0061" last-cp="007A"
      comment="LATIN SMALL LETTER A - LATIN SMALL LETTER Z" /&gt;
&lt;/data&gt;
&lt;/lgr></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>
            <t>The following sample LGR shows a more complete collection of the elements and
                attributes defined in this specification in a somewhat typical context.</t>
            <t>
                <figure>
<artwork>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;

&lt;!-- This example uses a large subset of the features of this
     specification. It does not include every set operator,
     match operator element, or action trigger attribute, their 
     use being largely parallel to the ones demonstrated. --&gt;

&lt;lgr xmlns="http://www.iana.org/lgr/0.1"&gt;
&lt;!-- meta element with all optional elements --&gt;
  &lt;meta&gt;
    &lt;version comment="initial version"&gt;1&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;date&gt;2010-01-01&lt;/date&gt;
    &lt;language&gt;sv&lt;/language&gt;
    &lt;domain&gt;example&lt;/domain&gt;
    &lt;validity-start&gt;2010-01-01&lt;/validity-start&gt;
    &lt;validity-end&gt;2013-12-31&lt;/validity-end&gt;
    &lt;description type="text/html"&gt;
        &lt;![CDATA[
        This language table was developed with the
        &lt;a href="http://swedish.example/"&gt;Swedish
        examples institute&lt;/a&gt;.
        ]]&gt;
    &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;unicode-version&gt;6.3.0&lt;/unicode-version&gt;
    &lt;references&gt;
      &lt;reference id="0" comment="the most recent" &gt;The
            Unicode Standard 6.2&lt;/reference&gt;
      &lt;reference id="1" &gt;RFC 5892&lt;/reference&gt;
      &lt;reference id="2" &gt;Big-5: Computer Chinese Glyph
         and Character Code Mapping Table, Technical Report
         C-26, 1984&lt;/reference&gt;
    &lt;/references&gt;
 &lt;/meta&gt;
 &lt;!-- the data section describing the repertoire --&gt;
  &lt;data&gt;
    &lt;!-- single code point "char" element --&gt;
    &lt;char cp="002D" ref="1" comment="HYPHEN" /&gt;

    &lt;!-- range elements for contiguous code points,  with tags --&gt;
    &lt;range first-cp="0030" last-cp="0039" ref="1" tag="digit" /&gt;
    &lt;range first-cp="0061" last-cp="007A" ref ="1" tag="letter" /&gt;

    &lt;!-- code point sequence --&gt;
    &lt;char cp="006C 00B7 006C" comment="catalan middle dot" /&gt;

    &lt;!-- alternatively use a when rule --&gt;
    &lt;char cp="00B7" when="catalan-middle-dot" /&gt;

     &lt;!-- code point with context rule --&gt;
    &lt;char cp="200D" when="joiner" ref="2" /&gt;

    &lt;!-- code points with variants --&gt;
    &lt;char cp="4E16" tag="preferred" ref="0"&gt;
      &lt;var cp="4E17" type="block" ref="2" /&gt;
      &lt;var cp="534B" type="allocate" ref="2" /&gt;
    &lt;/char&gt;
    &lt;char cp="4E17" ref="0"&gt;
      &lt;var cp="4E16" type="allocate" ref="2" /&gt;
      &lt;var cp="534B" type="allocate" ref="2" /&gt;
    &lt;/char&gt;
    &lt;char cp="534B" ref="0"&gt;
      &lt;var cp="4E16" type="allocate" ref="2" /&gt;
      &lt;var cp="4E17" type="block" ref="2" /&gt;
    &lt;/char&gt;
  &lt;/data&gt;

  &lt;!-- Context and whole label rules --&gt;
  &lt;rules&gt;
    &lt;!-- Require the given code point to be between two 006C --&gt;
    &lt;rule name="catalan-middle-dot" ref="0"&gt;
        &lt;look-behind&gt;
            &lt;char cp="006C" /&gt;
        &lt;/look-behind&gt;
        &lt;anchor /&gt;
        &lt;look-ahead&gt;
            &lt;char cp="006C" /&gt;
        &lt;/look-ahead&gt;
    &lt;/rule&gt;

    &lt;!-- example of a context rule based on property --&gt;
    &lt;class name="virama" property="ccc:9" /&gt;
    &lt;rule name="joiner"  ref="1" &gt;
        &lt;look-behind&gt;
            &lt;class by-ref="virama" /&gt;
        &lt;/look-behind&gt;
        &lt;anchor /&gt;
    &lt;/rule&gt;

    &lt;!-- example of using set operators --&gt;

    &lt;!-- Subtract vowels from letters to get
         consonant, demonstrating the different 
         set notations and the difference operator --&gt;
    &lt;difference name="consonants"&gt;
         &lt;class comment="all letters"&gt;0061-007A&lt;/class&gt;
         &lt;class comment="all vowels"&gt;
                 0061 0065 0069 006F 0075
         &lt;/class&gt;
     &lt;/difference&gt;

     &lt;!-- by using the start and end, rule matches whole label --&gt;
     &lt;rule name="three-or-more-consonants"&gt;
         &lt;start /&gt;
         &lt;!-- reference the class defined by the difference
              and require three or more matches --&gt;
         &lt;class by-ref="consonants" count="3+" /&gt;
         &lt;end /&gt;
    &lt;/rule&gt;

    &lt;!-- rule for negative matching --&gt;
    &lt;rule name="non-preferred"
          comment="matches any non-preferred code point"&gt;
        &lt;complement comment="non-preferred" &gt;
            &lt;class from-tag="preferred" /&gt;
        &lt;/complement&gt;
    &lt;/rule&gt;

   &lt;!-- actions triggered by matching rules and/or 
        variant types --&gt;
    &lt;action disp="consonants" 
            match="three-or-more-consonants" /&gt;
    &lt;action disp="block" any-variant="block" /&gt;
    &lt;action disp="activate" all-variants="allocate"
            not-match="non-preferred" /&gt;
  &lt;/rules&gt;
&lt;/lgr&gt;</artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="How to Translate RFC 3743 based Tables into the XML Format"
            anchor="translate_rfc3743">

            <t>As a background, the <xref target="RFC3743"/> rules work as follows:</t>
            <t>
                <list style="numbers">
                    <t>The Original (requested) label is checked to make sure that all the code
                        points are a subset of the repertoire.</t>
                    <t>If it passes the check, the Original label is allocatable.</t>
                    <t>Generate the all-simplified and all-traditional variant labels (union of all
                        the labels generated using all the simplified variants of the code points)
                        for allocation.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t> To illustrate by example, here is one of the more complicated set of variants: </t>
            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[    U+4E7E
    U+4E81
    U+5E72
    U+5E79
    U+69A6
    U+6F27 ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>
            <t>The following shows the relevant section of the Chinese language table published by
                the .ASIA registry <xref target="ASIA-TABLE"/>. Its entries read:</t>
            <t>
                <figure>
<artwork><![CDATA[ <codepoint>;<simpl-variant(s)>;<trad-variant(s)>;<other-variant(s)>]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>
            <t>These are the lines corresponding to the set of variants listed above</t>
            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[U+4E7E;U+4E7E,U+5E72;U+4E7E;U+4E81,U+5E72,U+6F27,U+5E79,U+69A6
U+4E81;U+5E72;U+4E7E;U+5E72,U+6F27,U+5E79,U+69A6
U+5E72;U+5E72;U+5E72,U+4E7E,U+5E79;U+4E7E,U+4E81,U+69A6,U+6F27
U+5E79;U+5E72;U+5E79;U+69A6,U+4E7E,U+4E81,U+6F27
U+69A6;U+5E72;U+69A6;U+5E79,U+4E7E,U+4E81,U+6F27
U+6F27;U+4E7E;U+6F27;U+4E81,U+5E72,U+5E79,U+69A6]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>

            <t> The corresponding data section XML format would look like this:</t>
            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[    <data>
    <char cp="4E7E">
    <var cp="4E7E" type="both" comment="identity" />
    <var cp="4E81" type="block" />
    <var cp="5E72" type="simp" />
    <var cp="5E79" type="block" />
    <var cp="69A6" type="block" />
    <var cp="6F27" type="block" />
    </char>
    <char cp="4E81">
    <var cp="4E7E" type="trad" />
    <var cp="5E72" type="simp" />
    <var cp="5E79" type="block" />
    <var cp="69A6" type="block" />
    <var cp="6F27" type="block" />
    </char>
    <char cp="5E72">
    <var cp="4E7E" type="trad"/>
    <var cp="4E81" type="block"/>
    <var cp="5E72" type="both" comment="identity"/>
    <var cp="5E79" type="trad"/>
    <var cp="69A6" type="block"/>
    <var cp="6F27" type="block"/>
    </char>
    <char cp="5E79">
    <var cp="4E7E" type="block"/>
    <var cp="4E81" type="block"/>
    <var cp="5E72" type="simp"/>
    <var cp="5E79" type="trad" comment="identity"/>
    <var cp="69A6" type="block"/>
    <var cp="6F27" type="block"/>
    </char>
    <char cp="69A6">
    <var cp="4E7E" type="block"/>
    <var cp="4E81" type="block"/>
    <var cp="5E72" type="simp"/>
    <var cp="5E79" type="block"/>
    <var cp="69A6" type="trad" comment="identity"/>
    <var cp="6F27" type="block"/>
    </char>
    <char cp="6F27">
    <var cp="4E7E" type="simp"/>
    <var cp="4E81" type="block"/>
    <var cp="5E72" type="block"/>
    <var cp="5E79" type="block"/>
    <var cp="69A6" type="block"/>
    <var cp="6F27" type="trad" comment="identity"/>
    </char>
  </data>]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>

            <t>Here the simplified variants have been given a type of "simp", the
                traditional variants one of "trad" and all other ones are given "block". </t>
            <t>Because some variant mappings show in more than one column, while the
               XML format allows only a single type value, they have been given the
               type of "both".</t>
            <t> Note that some variant mappings map to themselves (identity), that is the mapping is
                reflexive (see <xref target="reflexive_mapping"/>). In creating the permutation of
                all variant labels, these mappings have no effect, other than adding a value to the
                variant type list for the variant label containing them. </t>
            <t>In the example so far, all of the entries with type="both" are also mappings where
                source and target are identical. That is, they are reflexive mappings as defined in
                <xref target="reflexive_mapping" />. </t>
            <t> Given a label "U+4E7E U+4E81", the following labels would be ruled allocatable under
                    <xref target="RFC3743"/> based on how that standard is commonly implemented in
                domain registries:</t>
            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[    Original label:     U+4E7E U+4E81
    Simplified label 1: U+4E7E U+5E72
    Simplified label 2: U+5E72 U+5E72
    Traditional label:  U+4E7E U+4E7E]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>
            <t>However, if  allocatable labels were generated simply by a straight permutation
                of all variants with type other than type="block" and without regard to the
                simplified / traditional variants, we would end up with an extra allocatable
                label of "U+5E72 U+4E7E". This label is comprised of a both Simplified Chinese
                character and a Traditional Chinese code point and therefore shouldn't be
                allocatable.</t>
            <t>To more fully resolve the dispositions requires several actions to be defined as
                described in <xref target="rfc3743_example" /> which will override the default
                actions from <xref target="default_actions" />. After blocking all labels that
                contain a variant with type "block", these actions will allocate labels based
                on the following variant types: "simp", "trad" and "both". Note that
                these variant types do not directly relate to dispositions for the variant label,
                but that the actions will resolve them to the standard dispositions on labels,
                to with "block" and "allocate".</t>
            <t>To resolve label dispositions requires five actions to be defined (in the rules
                section of this document) these actions apply in order and the first one
                triggered, defines the disposition for the label. The actions are:
            <list style="numbers">
                <t>block all variant labels containing at least one blocked variant.</t>
                <t>allocate all labels that consist entirely of variants that are "simp" or
                    "both"</t>
                <t>also allocate all labels that are entirely "trad" or "both"</t>
                <t>block all surviving labels containing any one of the dispositions "simp"
                    or "trad" or "both" because they are now known to be part of an undesirable
                    mixed simplified/traditional label</t>
                <t>allocate any remaining label; the original label would be such a label.</t>
            </list>
            </t>
            <t>The rules declarations would be represented as:</t>
<t><figure><artwork><![CDATA[  <rules>
    <!--Action elements - order defines precedence-->
    <action disp="block"     any-variant="block" />
    <action disp="allocate"  only-variants="simp both" />
    <action disp="allocate"  only-variants="trad both" />
    <action disp="block"     any-variant="simp trad" />
    <action disp="allocate"  comment="catch-all" />
  </rules>]]></artwork></figure></t>

            <t>Up to now, variants with type "both" have occurred only associated with reflexive
                variant mappings. The "action" elements defined above rely on the assumption
                that this is always the case. However, consider the following set of variants:
            </t>
            <t><figure><artwork><![CDATA[    U+62E0;U+636E;U+636E;U+64DA
    U+636E;U+636E;U+64DA;U+62E0
    U+64DA;U+636E;U+64DA;U+62E0]]></artwork></figure></t>
            <t>The corresponding XML would be:</t>
 <t><figure><artwork><![CDATA[    <char cp="62E0">
    <var cp="636E" type="both" comment="both, but not reflexive" />
    <var cp="64DA" type="block" />
    </char>
    <char cp="636E">
    <var cp="636E" type="simp" comment="reflexive, but not both" />
    <var cp="64DA" type="trad" />
    <var cp="62E0" type="block" />
    </char>
    <char cp="64DA">
    <var cp="636E" type="simp" />
    <var cp="64DA" type="trad" comment="reflexive" />
    <var cp="62E0" type="block" />
    </char>]]></artwork></figure></t>

            <t>To make such variant sets work requires a way to selectively trigger an
                action based on whether a variant type is associated with an identity
                or reflexive mapping, or is associated with an ordinary variant mapping.
                This can be done by adding a prefix "r-" to the "type" attribute on
                reflexive variant mappings. For example the "trad" for code point U+64DA
                in the preceding figure would become "r-trad".</t>
            <t>With the dispositions prepared in this way, only a slight modification to
                the actions is needed to yield the correct set of allocatable labels:</t>

 <t><figure><artwork><![CDATA[  <action disp="block" any-variant="block" />
  <action disp="allocate" only-variants="simp r-simp both r-both" />
  <action disp="allocate" only-variants="trad r-trad both r-both" />
  <action disp="block" all-variants="simp trad both" />
  <action disp="allocate" />
]]></artwork></figure></t>

            <t>The first three actions get triggered by the same labels as before.</t>

            <t>The fourth action blocks any label that combines an original code point
                with any mix of ordinary variant mappings; however no labels that are a
                combination of only original code points (code points having either no
                variant mappings or a reflexive mapping) would be affected. These are
                the original labels and they are allocated in the last action.</t>

            <t>Using this scheme of assinging types to ordinary and reflexive variants,
                all RFC 3743-style tables can be converted to XML. By defining a set of
                actions as outlined above, the LGR will yield the correct set of
                allocatable variants:  all variants consisting completely of variant
                code points preferred for simplified or traditional, respectively, will
                be allocated, as will be the original label. All other variant labels
                will be blocked.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Indic Syllable Structure Example" anchor="indic_syllable">

            <t> In LGRs for Indic scripts it may be desirable to restrict valid labels to sequences
                of valid Indic syllables, or aksharas. This appendix gives a sample set of rules
                designed to enforce this restriction. </t>
            <t>We start with the following BNF form for an akshara which has been published in
                Devanagari Script Behavior for Hindi" <xref target="TDIL-HINDI"/> but which, if not
                directly valid for other languages and scripts used in India is at least similar to
                equivalent definitions used for them.</t>

            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[    V[m]|{C[N]H}C[N](H|[v][m])]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>

            <t>Where:</t>
            <t>
                <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                    <t hangText="V">(upper case) is any independent vowel</t>
                    <t hangText="m"> is any vowel modifier (Devanagari Anusvara, Visarga, and
                        Candrabindu)</t>
                    <t hangText="C"> is any consonant (with inherent vowel)</t>
                    <t hangText="N"> is Nukta</t>
                    <t hangText="H"> is a Halant (or Virama)</t>
                    <t hangText="v"> (lower case) is any dependent vowel sign (matra)</t>
                    <t hangText="{}"> encloses items which may be repeated one or more times</t>
                    <t hangText="[ ]"> encloses items which may or may not be present</t>
                    <t hangText="|"> separates items, out of which only one can be present</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t> By using the Unicode property "InSC" or "Indic_Syllable_Category" which corresponds
                rather directly to the classification of characters in the BNF above, we can
                directly translate the BNF into a set of WLE rules matching the definition of an
                akshara.</t>

            <t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork><![CDATA[ <rules>
    <!--Character Class Definitions go here-->
    <class name="halant" property="InSC:Virama" />
    <union name="vowel-modifier">
      <class property="InSC:Visarga" />
      <class property="InSC:Bindu" comment="includes anusvara" />
    </union>
    <!--Whole label evaluation and Context rules go here-->
    <rule name="consonant-with-optional-nukta">
        <class by-ref="InSC:Consonant" />
        <class by-ref="InSC:Nukta"  count="0:1"/>
    </rule>
    <rule name="independent-vowel-with-optional-modifier">
        <class by-ref="InSC:Vowel_Independent" />
        <class by-ref="vowel-modifier"  count="0:1" />
    </rule>
    <rule name="optional-dependent-vowel-with-opt-modifier" >
      <class by-ref="InSC:Vowel_Dependent" count="0:1" />
      <class by-ref="vowel-modifier" count="0:1"  />
    </rule>
    <rule name="consonant-cluster">
      <rule count="0+">
        <rule by-ref="consonant-with-optional-nukta" />
        <class by-ref="halant" />
      </rule>
      <rule by-ref="consonant-with-optional-nukta" />
      <choice>
        <class by-ref="halant" />
        <rule by-ref="optional-dependent-vowel-with-opt-modifier" />
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="akshara">
      <choice>
        <rule by-ref="independent-vowel-with-optional-modifier" />
        <rule by-ref="consonant-cluster" />
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="WLE-akshara-or-other" comment="series of one or
        more aksharas, possibly alternating with other types of
        code points such as digits">
      <start />
      <choice count="1+">
        <class property="InSC:other"  />
        <rule by-ref="akshara"  />
      </choice>
      <end />
    </rule>
    <!--Action elements go here - order defines precedence-->
    <action disp="invalid" not-match="WLE-akshara-or-other" />
  </rules>]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </t>

            <t> With the rules and classes as defined above, the final action assigns a disposition
                of "invalid" to all labels that are not composed of a sequence of well-formed
                aksharas, optionally interspersed with other characters, perhaps digits, for
                example.</t>

            <t> The relevant Unicode property is as of this writing still considered provisional;
                however, it could be replicated by tagging repertoire values directly in the LGR
                which would remove the dependency on the Unicode Standard altogether. </t>
        </section>

        <section title="RelaxNG Compact Schema">
            <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
default namespace = "http://www.iana.org/lgr/0.1"

#
# SIMPLE TYPES
#

# RFC 5646 language tag (e.g. "de", "und-Latn", etc.)
language-tag = xsd:token

# The scope to which the LGR applies. For the "domain" scope type it
# should be a fully qualified domain name.
scope-value = xsd:token {
    minLength = "1"
}

## a single code point
code-point = xsd:token {
    pattern = "[0-9A-F]{4,6}"
}

## a space-separated sequence of code points
code-point-sequence = xsd:token {
    pattern = "[0-9A-F]{4,6}( [0-9A-F]{4,6})+"
}

## single code point, or a sequence of code points
code-point-literal = code-point | code-point-sequence

code-point-set-shorthand = xsd:token {
    pattern = "([0-9A-F]{4,6}|[0-9A-F]{4,6}-[0-9A-F]{4,6})"
              ~ "( ([0-9A-F]{4,6}|[0-9A-F]{4,6}-[0-9A-F]{4,6}))*"
}

## dates are used in information fields in the meta section.
date = xsd:token {
    pattern = "\d{4}-\d\d-\d\d"
}

## reference to a rule name (used in "when" and "not-when"
## attributes, as well as the "by-ref" attribute of the "rule"
## element.)
rule-ref = xsd:IDREF

## a space-separated list of tags. Tags should generally follow
## xsd:Name syntax. However, we are using the xsd:NMTOKENS here
## because there is no native XSD datatype for space-separated
## xsd:Name
tags = xsd:NMTOKENS

## The value space of a "from-tag" attribute. Although it is closer
## to xsd:IDREF lexically and semantically, tags are not unique in
## the document. As such, we are unable to take advantage of
## facilities provided by a validator. xsd:NMTOKEN is used instead
## of the stricter xsd:Names here so as to be consistent with the
## above.
tag-ref = xsd:NMTOKEN

## an identifier type (used by "name" attributes).
identifier = xsd:ID

## used in the class "by-ref" attribute to reference another class
## of
## the same "name" attribute value.
class-ref = xsd:IDREF

## count attribute pattern ("n", "n+" or "n:m")
count-pattern = xsd:token {
    pattern = "\d+(\+|:\d+)?"
}

#
# STRUCTURES
#

## Representation of a single code point, or a sequence of code
## points
char = element char {
    attribute cp { code-point-literal },
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute when { rule-ref }?,
    attribute not-when { rule-ref }?,
    attribute tag { tags }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    variant*
}

## Representation of a range of code points
range = element range {
    attribute first-cp { code-point },
    attribute last-cp { code-point },
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute tag { tags }?,
    attribute ref { text }?
}

## Representation of a single code point (no sequences allowed, and
## no tag attribute allowed). This is used when defining the set of
## characters that constitute a class.
char-simple = element char {
    attribute cp { code-point }
}

## Representation of a range of code points, for use in defining the
## set of characters that constitute a class.
range-simple = element range {
    attribute first-cp { code-point },
    attribute last-cp { code-point }
}


## Representation of a variant code point or sequence
variant = element var {
    attribute cp { code-point-literal },
    attribute type { text }?,
    attribute when { rule-ref }?,
    attribute not-when { rule-ref }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute type { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?
}


#
# Classes
#


## a "class" element that references the name of another "class"
## (or set-operator like "union") defined elsewhere.
## If used as a matcher (appearing under a "rule" ## element),
## the "count" attribute may be present.
class-invocation = element class {
    (attribute by-ref { class-ref }
        | attribute from-tag { tag-ref }),
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    attribute comment { text }?
}

## defines a new class (set of code points) using Unicode property or
## code point literals
class-declaration = element class {
    # "name" attribute MUST be present if this is a "top-level" class
    # declaration, i.e. appearing directly under the "rules" element.
    # Otherwise, it MUST be absent.
    attribute name { identifier }?,
    # If used as a matcher (appearing in a "rule" element), the
    # "count" attribute may be present. Otherwise, it MUST be absent.
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    (
      # define the class by property (e.g. property="sc:Latn"), OR
      attribute property { text }
      # define the class by tagged code points, OR
      | attribute from-tag { tag-ref }
      # list of single code points and ranges, OR
      | (char-simple | range-simple)+
      # text node to allow for shorthand notation e.g.
      # "0061 0062-0063"
      | code-point-set-shorthand
    )
  }

class-or-set-operator-nested =
  class-invocation | class-declaration | set-operator

class-or-set-operator-declaration =
  # a "class" element or set operator (effectively defining a class)
  # directly in the "rules" element.
  class-declaration | set-operator


#
# Set operators
#

complement-operator = element complement {
    attribute name { identifier }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    # "count" attribute MUST only be used when this set-operator is
    # used as a matcher (i.e. nested in a <rule> element)
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    class-or-set-operator-nested
}

union-operator = element union {
    attribute name { identifier }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    # "count" attribute MUST only be used when this set-operator is
    # used as a matcher (i.e. nested in a <rule> element)
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    class-or-set-operator-nested,
    # needs two or more child elements
    class-or-set-operator-nested+
}

intersection-operator = element intersection {
    attribute name { identifier }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    # "count" attribute MUST only be used when this set-operator is
    # used as a matcher (i.e. nested in a <rule> element)
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    class-or-set-operator-nested,
    class-or-set-operator-nested
}

difference-operator = element difference {
    attribute name { identifier }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    # "count" attribute MUST only be used when this set-operator is
    # used as a matcher (i.e. nested in a <rule> element)
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    class-or-set-operator-nested,
    class-or-set-operator-nested
}

symmetric-difference-operator = element symmetric-difference {
    attribute name { identifier }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    # "count" attribute MUST only be used when this set-operator is
    # used as a matcher (i.e. nested in a <rule> element)
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    class-or-set-operator-nested,
    class-or-set-operator-nested
}

## operators that transform class(es) into a new class.
set-operator = complement-operator
               | union-operator
               | intersection-operator
               | difference-operator
               | symmetric-difference-operator

#
# Match operators (matchers)
#

any-matcher = element any {
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    attribute comment { text }?
}

choice-matcher = element choice {
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    # two or more match operators
    match-operator-choice,
    match-operator-choice+
}

char-matcher =
  # for use as a matcher - like "char" but without a "tag" attribute
  element char {
    attribute cp { code-point-literal },
    # If used as a matcher (appearing in a "rule" element), the
    # "count" attribute may be present. Otherwise, it MUST be
    # absent.
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?
}

start-matcher = element start {
    attribute comment { text }?
}

end-matcher = element end {
    attribute comment { text }?
}

anchor-matcher = element anchor {
    attribute comment { text }?
}

look-ahead-matcher = element look-ahead {
    attribute comment { text }?,
    match-operators-non-pos
}
look-behind-matcher = element look-behind {
    attribute comment { text }?,
    match-operators-non-pos
}

## non-positional match operator that can be used as a
## direct child element of the choice matcher.
match-operator-choice = (
  any-matcher | choice-matcher | start-matcher | end-matcher
  | char-matcher | class-or-set-operator-nested | rule-matcher
)

## non-positional match operators do not contain any anchor,
## look-behind or look-ahead elements.
match-operators-non-pos = (
  start-matcher?,
  (any-matcher | choice-matcher | char-matcher
   | class-or-set-operator-nested | rule-matcher)*,
  end-matcher?
)

## positional match operators have an anchor element, which may be
## preceeded by a look-behind element, or followed by a look-ahead
## element, or both.
match-operators-pos =
  look-behind-matcher?, anchor-matcher, look-ahead-matcher?

match-operators = match-operators-non-pos | match-operators-pos


#
# Rules
#

# top-level rule must have "name" attribute
rule-declaration-top = element rule {
    attribute name { identifier },
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    match-operators
}

## rule element used as a matcher (either by-ref or contains other
## match operators itself)
rule-matcher =
  element rule {
    attribute count { count-pattern }?,
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    (attribute by-ref { rule-ref } | match-operators)
  }


#
# Actions
#

action-declaration = element action {
    attribute comment { text }?,
    attribute ref { text }?,
    attribute disp { text },
    ( attribute match { text } | attribute not-match { text } )?,
    ( attribute any-variant { text }
      | attribute all-variants { text }
      | attribute only-variants { text } )?
}

# DOCUMENT STRUCTURE

start = lgr
lgr = element lgr {
    attribute id { text }?,
    meta-section?,
    data-section,
    rules-section?
}


## Meta section - information recorded with an label
## generation ruleset that generally does not affect machine
## processing (except for unicode-version). However, if any
## "class-declaration" uses the "property" attribute, one or
## more unicode-version MUST be present.

meta-section = element meta {
    element version {
        attribute comment { text }?,
        text
    }?
    & element date {
        xsd:token {
            pattern = "\d{4}-\d{2}-\d{2}"
        }
    }?
    & element language { language-tag }*
    & element scope {
        # type may by "domain" or an application-defined value
        attribute type { xsd:NCName },
        scope-value
    }*
    & element validity-start { text }?
    & element validity-end { text }?
    & element unicode-version {
        xsd:token {
            pattern = "\d+\.\d+\.\d+"
        }
    }?
    & element description {
        attribute type { text }?,
        text
    }?
    & element references {
        element reference {
            attribute id { text },
            attribute comment { text }?,
            text
        }*
    }?
}

data-section = element data { (char | range)+ }

## Note that action declarations are strictly order dependent.
## class-or-set-operator-declaration and rule-declaration-top
## are weakly order dependent, they must precede first use of the
## identifier via by-ref.
rules-section = element rules {
  ( class-or-set-operator-declaration
    | rule-declaration-top
    | action-declaration)*
}

]]></artwork>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>This format builds upon the work on documenting IDN tables by many different registry
                operators. Notably, a comprehensive language table for Chinese, Japanese and Korean
                was developed by the "Joint Engineering Team" <xref target="RFC3743"/> that is the
                basis of many registry policies; and a set of guidelines for Arabic script
                registrations <xref target="RFC5564"/> was published by the Arabic-language
                community. </t>
            <t>Contributions that have shaped this document have been provided by Francisco Arias,
                Mark Davis, Paul Hoffman, Nicholas Ostler, Thomas Roessler, Steve Sheng, Michel
                Suignard, Andrew Sullivan, Wil Tan and John Yunker. </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Editorial Notes">
            <t>This appendix to be removed prior to final publication.</t>

            <section title="Known Issues and Future Work">

                <t>
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>A method of specifying the origin URI for a table, and an expiration or
                            refresh policy, as meta-data may be a useful way to declare how the
                            table will be updated.</t>
                        <t>The "domain" element should be specified as absolute, so that the Root
                            can be identified as needed for the Root Zone LGR.</t>

                        <t>The recommended names for disposition ("block" and "allocate") deviate
                            from the name in the Root Zone LGR Procedure ("blocked" and
                            "allocatable"). The latter were chosen to highlight that the machine
                            processing of the LGR table is just the first step, actual allocation
                            requires additional actions, hence "allocatable". This should be
                            resolved.</t>


                    </list>
                </t>

            </section>

            <section title="Change History">
                <t>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-00">Initial draft.</t>
                    </list>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-01">Add an XML Namespace, and fix other XML nits. Add support
                            for sequences of code points. Improve on consistently using Unicode
                            nomenclature. </t>
                    </list>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-02">Add support for validity periods.</t>
                    </list>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-03">Incorporate requirements from the Label Generation Ruleset
                            Procedure for the DNS Root Zone. These requirements include a detailed
                            grammar for specifying whole-label variants, and the ability to
                            explicitly declare of the actions associated with a specific variant.
                            The document also consistently applies the term "Label Generation
                            Ruleset", rather than "IDN table", to reflect the policy term now being
                            used to describe these. </t>
                    </list>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-04">Support reference information per <xref target="RFC3743"
                            />. Update description in response to feedback. Extend the context rules
                            to "char" elements and allow for inverse matching ("not-when"). Extend
                            the description of label processing and implied actions, and allow for
                            actions that reference disposition attributes on any or all variant
                            mappings used in the generation of a variant label. </t>
                    </list>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-05">Change the name of the "disposition" attribute to "disp".
                            Add comment attribute on version and reference elements. Allow empty
                            "cp" attributes in char elements to support expressing symmetric mapping
                            of null variants. Describe use of variants that map identically. Clarify
                            how actions are triggered, in particular based on variant dispositions,
                            as well as description of default actions. Revise description of
                            processing a label and its variants. Move example table at the head of
                            appendices. Add "only-variants" attribute. Change "name" attribute to
                            "by-ref" attribute for referencing named classes and rules. Change "not"
                            to "complement". Remove "match" attribute on rules as redundant if
                            "start" and "end" are supported. Rename "match" element to "anchor" as
                            better fitting it's function and removing confusion with both the
                            "match" attribute on actions as well as the generic term Match Operator.
                            Augmented the examples relevant to <xref target="RFC3743"/>.</t>
                    </list>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-06">Extend the discussion of reflexive variants and their use;
                            includes update of the appendix on converting tables in the style of
                                <xref target="RFC3743"/>. Improve description of tagging and clarify
                            that it doesn't apply to sequences. Specify that root zone uses ".". Add
                            an appendix with an Indic Syllable Structure example. Extend count
                            attribute to allow maximal counts.</t>
                    </list>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-07">Change "byref" to "by-ref". Add list of recommended
                            properties. Change "location" to "positional" for collective name of
                            start/end match operators. Use from-tag instead of by-ref for tag-based
                            classes. Made optional or mutually exclusive nature of some attributes
                            more explicit. Allowing "comment" attributes on all child elements of
                            "rules" except "char" and "range" elements used as child elements of
                            "class". Recast the design goals and requirements at the start of the
                            document. Reword aspects of the document to make it clear the format's
                            application is not limited only to domain names.</t>
                    </list>
                    <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
                        <t hangText="-08">Change "domain" to scope with type="domain". Reword in
                            several places for clarity. Flesh out note on security. Change "disp"
                            to "type" for variants, to mark that these attributes do not necessarily
                            correspond one-to-one to variant label dispositions. Add example of
                            variant type triggers.  Remove "long form" of class definition.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
    </back>

</rfc>
