<?xml version="1.0"?>
<idntable xmlns="http://www.iana.org/idn-tables/0.1">
  <meta>
    <language>ko</language>
    <domain>asia</domain>
    <date>2011-05-04</date>
    <version>1.1</version>
    <description type="text/plain">&#65279;.ASIA KO IDN Language Table

TLD: ASIA
Version: 1.0
Effective Date: 2011-03-11

Summary of IDN Policy Profile:
IDN LangaugeTag: KO
IDN Language Description: Korean
Minimum Length: A-Label: 3; U-Label: 1
Maximum Length: A-Label: 63
Valid Characters: 11,209
Additional Contextual Rules: A Domain Name Applied For must include at least one non-LDH character
IDN Variants: N/A

Registry: DotAsia Organisation
Contact: DotAsia Admin Contact &lt;admin@iana.whois.asia&gt;
Contact: DotAsia Tech Contact &lt;tech@iana.whois.asia&gt;
Address: 15/F, 6 Knutsford Terrace, Tsim Sha Tsui, Hong Kong
TEL: +852.35202635
FAX: +852.35202634
Website: http://www.registry.asia

Relevant Policy Document URLs:
- .ASIA IDN Policies for CJK (Chinese, Japanese &amp; Korean): http://dot.asia/policies/DotAsia-CJK-IDN-
Policies-COMPLETE--2011-03-11.pdf
- .ASIA IDN Sunrise Policies: http://dot.asia/policies/DotAsia-IDN-Sunrise-Policies-COMPLETE--2011-
03-11.pdf


Abstract

This language table is adopted from the KRNIC Korean IDN Language table (ko-KR:
http://www.iana.org/domains/idn-tables/tables/kr_ko-kr_1.0.html) for the implementation of
Korean IDN registrations at the .ASIA gTLD.

DotAsia is committed to maintaining the integrity of .ASIA IDN registrations and understands the
multilingual nature of the .ASIA zone as a gTLD.  In preparation of this language table, DotAsia has
coordinated with KISA (Korea Internet &amp; Security Agency) on the applicability of the KRNIC Korean IDN
Language table for the .ASIA gTLD.

The following table includes 11,172 Hangul Syllables (along with the 36 LDH characters, &#8220;a-z&#8221;, &#8220;0-9&#8221; and
&#8220;-&#8220;) according to the consensus of Korean Internet community.  Hanja characters are not included in
the table.  Mixture of Hanja characters with Hangul characters for domain names is not encouraged.
Registrants interested in registering domain names with Hanja characters only may consider utilizing a
registration based on the ZH table.

The following table uses the RFC3743-defined format, and is in compliance with the ICANN Guidelines
for IDN registration and for publication in the IANA Repository of IDN Practices.

References:

Please refer to the references cited for the ko-KR KRNIC Korean IDN Language table.</description>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <range first-cp="0030" last-cp="0039" />
    <range first-cp="0061" last-cp="007A" />
    <range first-cp="AC00" last-cp="D7A3" />
  </data>
</idntable>