<?xml version="1.0"?>
<idntable xmlns="http://www.iana.org/idn-tables/0.1">
  <meta>
    <language>da-DK</language>
    <domain>museum</domain>
    <date>2004-10-01</date>
    <version>2.0</version>
    <description type="text/html">&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width="199"&gt; TLD: MUSEUM&lt;br&gt;
Language Tag: da-DK&lt;br&gt;
Language Description: Danish&lt;br&gt;
Version: 2.0&lt;br&gt;
Effective Date: 1 October 2004&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width="26"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width="33"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width="401"&gt; Registry: Museum Domain Management Association&lt;br&gt;
Contact: Cary Karp &lt;a href="mailto:admin@musedoma.museum"&gt;admin@musedoma.museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Address: Box 50007, SE-10405 Stockholm, Sweden&lt;br&gt;
Tel: +46 70 629 8176 Fax: +46 70 384 3246 &lt;br&gt;
Website: &lt;a href="http://musedoma.museum"&gt;http://musedoma.museum/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relevant Policy Document URL: http://about.museum/idn/idnpolicy.html&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This document describes the Internationalized Domain Names (IDN) Character
Table used by MuseDoma in the .MUSEUM TLD registry for the registration of .MUSEUM
domains in the Danish language. The policies for the application of this table
are described in detail in the document referenced above and are in compliance
with the ICANN Guidelines for the Implementation of Internationalized Domain
Names. The present document is intended for publication in the IANA IDN Character
Table Registry. It is provided exclusively for the information of prospective
holders of domains in .MUSEUM and for the users of resources within those domains.
It is not to be taken as a normative statement about the use of the Danish language
in any other context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Base characters are listed at the start of each line in this table by giving
their Unicode code points in U+xxxx format. If a base character is followed
by a vertical line &amp;quot;|&amp;quot;, the code point to the right of that line is
a variant of the base character. A hyphen &amp;quot;-&amp;quot; between code points
indicates a character string. Text appearing to the right of a number sign &amp;quot;#&amp;quot;
is an explanatory comment about a code point or group of code points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This table conforms to current Danish orthographic and lexicographic practice
as described by the Danish Language Council in the publication &amp;quot;Retskrivningsordbogen&amp;quot;
(Orthographic Dictionary), 3rd edition, 2001 (3rd printing, 2004). In addition
to the basic Danish alphabet, this authority recognizes foreign letters in proper
nouns and loan words and explicitly lists selected such characters in exemplification
of this. These characters are included in the present table for corresponding
illustrational purposes. The use of several diacritical marks applied to characters
in the basic Danish alphabet is also recognized but only selected resulting
code points are included in this table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlisted accented and foreign characters may be individually permitted in Danish
language domains in .MUSEUM if the requesting entity can demonstrate warrant
for doing so and the desired code points are explicitly included as base characters
in the character table for another language in the .MUSEUM &amp;quot;European language
group&amp;quot; as referenced in the policy document cited above. Danish belongs
to the European language group and the base characters listed below may be available
for use as foreign letters in other languages in that group, if doing so is
permitted in the narrative text in their respective character tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The character variants listed below are intended to call attention to situations
where confusion may arise if particular care is not taken to avoid it. No prescriptive
policies are attached to these character variants and the registration of a
domain containing one variant confers no rights to any other variant. All names
in .MUSEUM are subject to approval during an &amp;quot;Eligibility and Name Selection&amp;quot;
(ENS) process. Character variants are one of several factors considered to ensure
adequate differentiation between registered domains. The specific relevance
of variants will be determined for each domain during the ENS dialog within
a framework detailed in the policy statements for .MUSEUM, as described or referenced
in the policy document cited above.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <range first-cp="0030" last-cp="0039" />
    <range first-cp="0061" last-cp="0064" />
    <char cp="0065">
      <var cp="00E9" />
    </char>
    <range first-cp="0066" last-cp="007A" />
    <char cp="00E4" />
    <char cp="00E5">
      <var cp="0061 0061" />
    </char>
    <char cp="00E6" />
    <char cp="00E9">
      <var cp="0065" />
    </char>
    <char cp="00F0" />
    <char cp="00F6" />
    <char cp="00F8" />
    <char cp="00FC" />
    <char cp="00FE" />
  </data>
</idntable>