<?xml version="1.0"?>
<idntable xmlns="http://www.iana.org/idn-tables/0.1">
  <meta>
    <language>sv-SE</language>
    <domain>se</domain>
    <date>2006-11-21</date>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <description type="text/html">&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td width="250"&gt; TLD: SE&lt;br&gt;
Language Tag: sv-SE&lt;br&gt;
Language Description: Swedish&lt;br&gt;
Version: 1.0&lt;br&gt;
Effective Date: 21 November 2006&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width="26"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width="33"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width="360"&gt; Registry: .SE (Stiftelsen f&amp;ouml;r Internetinfrastruktur)&lt;br&gt;
Contact: Anne-Marie Eklund-L&amp;ouml;winder &lt;a href="mailto:Anne-Marie.Eklund-Lowinder@iis.se"&gt;Anne-Marie.Eklund-Lowinder@iis.se&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Address: Box 7399, SE-10391 Stockholm, Sweden&lt;br&gt;
Tel: +46 8 452 3500 Fax: +46 8 452 3502 &lt;br&gt;
Website: &lt;a href="http://www.iis.se"&gt;http://www.iis.se/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relevant Policy Document URL: &lt;a href="http://www.iis.se/pdf/allmanna_villkor_eng.pdf"&gt;http://www.iis.se/pdf/allmanna_villkor_eng.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document describes the character table used by the .SE registry for the
registration of domain names in the Swedish language and is intended for
publication in the IANA Repository of TLD IDN Practices. It is provided for the
information of prospective holders of domains in .SE and for the users of
resources within those domains. It is further intended to be a generally
applicable description of the character repertoire necessary for the inclusion
of Swedish language labels on all levels in other DNS registries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The material presented here was initially prepared by the .MUSEUM registry
and was posted as such in the IANA Repository (where it is now archived). The
present document is being substituted for it in collaboration with the .MUSEUM
registry, to indicate the Swedish language nexus more clearly. There are two
substantive differences between the versions. The first reflects an orthographic
reform that entered into effect in April 2006 and would, in any case, have
necessitated a revision of the previous table. The second is a simplification
in the description of alternate orthographic representations of characters that
lie outside the ASCII repertoire. The relevant policy document for the .MUSEUM
implementation is located at:
&lt;a href="http://about.museum/idn/idnpolicy.html"&gt;
http://about.museum/idn/idnpolicy.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This table conforms to current Swedish orthographic practice as described by
the Swedish Language Council in the publication &amp;quot;Svenska
spr&amp;aring;kregler&amp;quot;, 2nd edition, 2000 (2003 printing), and the
lexicographic practice documented by the Swedish Academy in the publication
&amp;quot;Svenska akademiens ordlista &amp;ouml;ver svenska spr&amp;aring;ket&amp;quot;, 13th
edition, first printing, 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Characters are listed in this table by their Unicode code points in U+xxxx
format. The name of each character appears to the right of the number
sign &amp;quot;#&amp;quot; on the same line. Explanatory comments about associated
orthographic conventions are similarly placed to the right of number signs. Any
narrative text about character variants is intended solely to call attention to
situations where confusion can arise if particular care is not taken to avoid it.
No prescriptive policies are attached to character variants in either the .SE
or .MUSEUM registries, and the registration of a label containing any of the listed
characters confers no rights to any other orthographically equivalent form. Other
registries wishing to implement this table are advised to take the discussion of
character variants solely for its informational value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <range first-cp="0030" last-cp="0039" />
    <range first-cp="0061" last-cp="007A" />
    <range first-cp="00E4" last-cp="00E5" />
    <char cp="00E9" />
    <char cp="00F6" />
    <char cp="00FC" />
  </data>
</idntable>