<?xml version="1.0"?>
<idntable xmlns="http://www.iana.org/idn-tables/0.1">
  <meta>
    <language>yi</language>
    <domain>se</domain>
    <date>2009-01-12</date>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <description type="text/html">&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
TLD: SE&lt;br&gt;
Language Tag: yi&lt;br&gt;
Language Description: Yiddish&lt;br&gt;

Version: 1.0&lt;br&gt;
Effective Date: 12 January 2009&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width="30"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td width="30"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
Registry: .SE (Stiftelsen f&amp;ouml;r Internetinfrastruktur)&lt;br&gt;
Contact: Anne-Marie Eklund-L&amp;ouml;winder &lt;a href="mailto:Anne-Marie.Eklund-Lowinder@iis.se"&gt;
Anne-Marie.Eklund-Lowinder@iis.se&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Address: Box 7399, SE-10391 Stockholm, Sweden&lt;br&gt;
Telephone: +46 8 452 3500 Fax: +46 8 452 3502&lt;br&gt;

Website: &lt;a href="http://www.iis.se//"&gt;http://www.iis.se/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Relevant Policy Document URL: &lt;a href="http://www.iis.se/pdf/allmanna_villkor_eng.pdf"&gt;
http://www.iis.se/pdf/allmanna_villkor_eng.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This document describes the language table used by the .SE registry for the registration of domain names in the
Yiddish language, which is one of the five legally recognized minority language in Sweden, and the only one
not written with the Latin script. The table presented here is in compliance with the ICANN Guidelines for the
Implementation of Internationalized Domain Names Version 2.1 and is intended for publication in the IANA
Repository of TLD IDN Practices, for the information of prospective holders of domains in .SE and for the users
of resources within those domains.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The material presented here was initially prepared by the .MUSEUM registry, which also supports the
registration of names using the following repertoire. A detailed explanation of the derivation of the
table, together with guidelines for name holders, is located
at &lt;a href="http://about.museum/idn/yiddish-language.pdf"&gt;http://about.museum/idn/yiddish-language.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Characters are listed in this table by their Unicode code points in U+xxxx format. The Unicode name for each
character appears to the right of the number sign "#" on the same line. Two consecutive code points on the
same line designate a base character with a combining mark.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A combining mark may only be used with a base character that it is explicitly associated with in the table.
A base character that only appears with a combining mark may not be used without that combining mark. A label
that includes a HEBREW LETTER may not contain a letter or equivalent character from any other script. Neither a
DIGIT nor a HYPHEN-MINUS may be placed in the initial or the final position in a label. Due to a restriction
imposed by the IDNA protocol, a character with a combining mark may not appear in the final position in a label.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No prescriptive policies are attached to what in differing orthographic traditions might be seen as character
variants, including characters that differ only by the presence or absence of a combining mark. The registration
of a label containing any of the listed characters confers no rights to any other orthographically comparable form.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <range first-cp="0030" last-cp="0039" />
    <range first-cp="05D0" last-cp="05EA" />
    <char cp="05F2" />
  </data>
</idntable>